getting to space is hard right now it's
like going up a mountain on a unicycle
with a backpack full of explosives
incredibly slow you can't transport a
lot of stuff and you might die a rocket
needs to reach a velocity of about
40,000 km hour to escape from Earth to
get to that speed Rockets are mostly
containers for fuel with a tiny tip of
payload this is bad if you want to go to
other planets because you need a lot of
heavy stuff if you want to survive and
maybe even come back so is there a way
to get a space with less Fuel and more
[Music]
payload a nice thing that solved most of
our transport problems on Earth is what
you call infrastructure whether it's
roads for cars ports for ships or rails
for trains we've made it easier to get
to places we can apply the same solution
to space travel space infrastructure
will make getting into orbit and Out To
The Moon Mars and Beyond easier and
cheaper great but what exactly is space
infrastructure unlike an Earth space
elevator which is currently science
fiction there is a simple yet promising
technology that does not require new
science magic materials or huge
Investments and that has been tested
successfully in orbit already a cable
and a weight known as a tether the
concept is so simple it's surprising
what if we put tethers hundreds or
thousands of kilom long into space and
had spacecraft use them as ladders to
climb to higher altitudes and gain
speed this concept is known as the
Skyhook it works even better if we make
it spin a counterweight holds a long
Cable in place while it rotates around a
circle a rotating tether slows down its
tip relative to the ground at the bottom
and speeds it up at the top like a
catapult this means that you can
transfer energy from the tether and get
a massive boost when released more or
less for free equal to twice the
tether's rotation velocity specialized
fibers already exist that can survive
the extraordinary stresses a Skyhook
would be faced with to protect against
cuts and collisions from debris and
meteorites we can thread our tether into
a web of redundant fibers since our
Skyhook would pass over the same spot
many times a day this would allow small
reusable shuttles to catch up with it of
course it's not that easy at its lowest
point the tether's tip is dashing
through the atmosphere at around 12,000
kmph because of Earth's atmosphere we
can't lower the sky hook too much or it
will get too hot from Air friction so it
will dip to a height of 80 to 150 km and
no lower to match this we'll need
specialized spacecraft that can get to
the tether while this isn't n exactly
easy it's still much cheaper than
getting a big Tin Can filled with rocket
fuel to go 40,000 km an hour catching
the tip will be a challenge too there's
only a short time window of 60 to 90
seconds to find a tiny thing in the sky
moving at Mark 12 to make this easier
the tip could have a sort of fishing
line a kilm long with a navigation drone
that helps the spacecraft connect
another challenge is keeping our Skyhook
in orbit as more and more ships patch
onto it and pull themselves up they use
up the momentum that keeps it in place
if we don't do anything it will slow
down and crash into the
atmosphere and here we can cheat the
universe a bit the Skyhook is a battery
of orbital energy it's possible to
balance the payloads coming in and being
sent off arriving ships bringing humans
and materials home to Earth add energy
to the tether which it can give to other
ships departing into space this way the
tether doesn't lose any energy the more
we use it the cheaper it gets if we're
still losing energy with each boost we
can recover it with small electric or
chemical engines that regularly correct
the tether's position a set of tethers
one around Earth and one around Mars
could make trips between the planets
fast straightforward and low cost
compared to Rockets the Earth tether
would sit in low earth orbit to grab
people and payloads and fling them off
to Mars the Mars tether catches them and
slows them down for a landing on the
surface Sur in the opposite direction
the tether could pick up a vehicle
traveling through Mars's thin atmosphere
at only about 1,000 km hour not much
faster than our airliners on Earth and
fling it back to Earth to be caught and
lowered down the tethers could shorten
trips between both planets from 9 months
down to 5 or even three and reduce the
scale of the Rockets required by between
84 and
96% even better people may be able to
travel in relative luxury as we could
afford to invest in passenger Comfort
tether travel would be first class seats
to Mars together tethers around Earth
and Mars could provide the rapid and
cost-efficient transportation backbone
that would make space travel affordable
but let's go further starting from low
Mars orbit a tether could boost ships to
the asteroid belt the first craft sent
to a new asteroid would need Rockets to
slow down at its destination subsequent
arrivals might find a tether waiting to
catch them and send them back for free
getting to asteroids cheaply is a major
factor in opening up the resources of
the solar system precious metals and
valuable minerals could be delivered to
Mars Just weeks after they were cut out
of their asteroid they would be the
perfect building blocks for our
interplanetary
civilization but why stop here Mars
moons are very convenient no other moons
in the solar system orbit that close to
their Planet Phobos is so heavy that we
don't need to worry about slowing it
down making it the perfect attachment
point for super tethers just under 6,000
km long the lower tip would fly just
over the surface of Mars and be very
easy to catch the upper tip can fling
ships all the way to Jupiter and Saturn
the same super tether can also bring the
inner solar system
closer Venus and Mercury are a single
swing away unlike Mars they're bursting
with solar energy and are rich in
minerals in the long term Nothing is
Stopping Humanity from constructing a
zero propellant transport Network for
the terrestrial planets centered on the
marsh and moons tethers are a comparably
cheap and sustainable solution to making
space travel affordable and the rest of
the soda system accessible for
exploitation and exploration considering
that we have the technology to build
them today there's really no good excuse
to wait any longer parts of the solar
system are far away but they could be
very close
oh