humans have existed for millions of
years as part of nature but then
something changed and in an incredibly
short amount of time we terraformed this
planet and designed it to fit our
needs as far as we know we're the first
beings to awaken and completely take
over a planet the transition from
hunting and Gathering to farming and
building was so breathtakingly fast that
many of our ways of thinking about the
world are no longer useful one of our
most outdated ideas is that the most
commonly used calendar in the world
insists that we live in the year
2016 this distorts our view of our own
history and makes it harder to
understand who we are as a species and
just how far we've come in an incredibly
short amount of time so maybe it's time
to choose a year zero for Humanity a
year zero that truly represents us as a
species and includes all cultures a year
zero that marks when we began building
our own world on top of the old
[Music]
one 12,000 years ago hundreds of humans
came together in the hills of Southern
Anatolia they were hunters and gatherers
without knowledge of Agriculture or
metal working all they had were tools
made of stone and wood but they built
built Humanity's first big construction
project 7,000 years before the pyramids
were built in Egypt spread over 300 M
our ancestors erected Circles of massive
Stone pillars each of them up to 6 M
high and 40 tons in weight decorated
with Artful pictograms and stone
carvings of animals and mythical
creatures we have no idea how they were
able to do this it was probably a
project of Epic scale for the Stone Age
requiring a level of or organization we
didn't know early humans were capable of
until we found this site so why did they
build it the most popular theory is that
this was the first temple of humanity
dedicated to long-forgotten
Gods we only know that this construction
project the first of its kind marks the
beginning of a new era it's in this area
around that time that humans truly began
to build their own world which would
make it a fitting milestone in our
history for the start of our
calendar this moment in time is so
distinct that scientists chesar Imani
proposed that Humanity should switch to
what he called the holos calendar by
adding 10,000 years to our current
Gregorian
calendar we don't need to change our
wellestablished days and months and
religious calendars could stay the same
as well but for all official purposes
our current year would be the year
126 of the human
ERA this would drastically alter how we
think about history and how it feels
let's take a very brief look and move
through our new history from our new
year
[Music]
zero 12,000 years ago saw the beginning
of the first construction project
kicking off our history it would be in
use for about 2,000 years it took nearly
a millennium until Jericho probably the
first city on Earth was founded in the
year 1000 after the start of the human
era progress was still very very slow at
this point over the next thousand years
more and more permanent settlements
appeared around the world and more and
more plants and animals were
domesticated as agriculture
spread evidence for trade over thousands
of kilometers has been found from this
period around 5 million humans were
alive at this point in history fewer
than live in London today technology
advanced con ly at a slow pace Pottery
became widespread the first cultural
communities appeared in China India and
the fertile present around the year
4,000 8,000 years ago from today humans
started to use metal for the first time
learning to mix tin and copper and
kickstarting what we know as the Bronze
Age around the year 5000 the first Proto
writing emerged and the wheel was
invented in South America the chincho
culture started to art artificially
mummify humans 2,000 years earlier than
in ancient
Egypt the first High cultures began
emerging around the year
7,000 the Indus Valley
Civilization ancient Egypt the Minoans
in Greece and the samarians in
Mesopotamia Stonehenge was built in
Britain and the first dynasty in China
begany the Iceman lived around this time
what we consider history now started and
things began picking up pace as the
world population Rose to over 30
million a number of new high cultures
appeared around the world many writing
down their
Legends more and more cities were
founded in South America the aleg
culture emerged around this time the
legendary Siege of Troy is supposed to
have happened soon after in the Eastern
Mediterranean and the fertile cresant
the Bronze Age ended in violence every
Bronze Age culture except Egypt was
destroyed by mysterious Invaders writing
and progress froze for hundreds of years
around the year
9,500 what we consider Western culture
began the Greek city states beat off the
Persian Invasion and triggered their
Golden Era ended by Alexander the Great
around
9,700 100 years later Rome destroyed
Carthage and became a dominant force in
the
world Caesar was murdered in the year
9,95 56 while the world population had
risen to about 300 million
people and it's only now around the year
10,000 that we've reached the point
where the Gregorian calendar and our
current method of marking human history
begins a mere 2,000 years from now
humans will walk on the moon if we think
about history as we do now we are
underplaying 10,000 years of human
progress and development including all
of it in our calendar makes our past
more impressive it shows how progress
became exponential with time and it
incorporates All Humans from all
cultures into our calendar a new year
zero for our history could reframe how
we think of
ourselves as a building project that
started 12,000 years ago when for the
first time our ancestors came together
to carve a temple out of bedrock with
tools made of stone not knowing what
they would set in motion
where it would lead us as a
species from building the first temple
to ships flying beyond the sky