until recently the vast majority of the
world population worked on farms and the
total production of the world's economy
was mostly the total agricultural output
and this output was limited by the fixed
size of the land the total output of the
economy did not change a lot year by
year
the size of the pie was fixed the world
was a zero-sum game
in such a stagnating world the only way
to get better off is if someone else
gets worse off
if you take a bigger piece of the pie
someone else's gets smaller
if you want more food then conquering
plundering and stealing are great
strategies your neighbor's loss is your
gain
this was the state of things for
thousands of years
societies invaded each other constantly
to get more pie
economic inequality was extreme
some had all the pie they wanted while
others had to live with the crumbs
then the industrial revolution happened
and everything changed
we developed machinery better crops
better fertilizers agricultural output
skyrocketed but we didn't just produce
more food every industrial sector
exploded in terms of productivity
from 1700 to 1870 the production of iron
in britain increased 137 fold
the industrial revolution led to a
previously unimaginable increase in
economic output
this altered the nature of our societies
economic growth changed the world from a
zero-sum game to a positive sum game
we had found a way to create a bigger
pie
but not only a bigger pie but a pie that
was growing bigger each year
more people could have more at the same
time
this development is spreading and
continuing today antibiotics kill
bacteria power plants deliver energy
cell phones connect us planes let us
travel cheaply fridges store food
continuous progress in all sectors of
the economy seems normal to us today but
the change from stagnation to economic
growth really was the most drastic shift
in human history how was this possible
at the very core of this massive
transformation stand new ideas that lead
to innovation
innovation has many different
definitions but in the context of this
video we mean better solutions to
existing problems and solutions to
problems we didn't know we had
the more you innovate the more complex
and interesting problems you discover as
your wishes and needs evolve
the average citizen in norway 250 years
ago might have wanted some really good
shoes
150 years ago maybe a bicycle 80 years
ago a car 30 years ago cheap air travel
and so on
once we get what we want we don't stop
we can see how we can improve things
even more and how to make things even
better
the new positive some world has existed
for 0.1 percent of human history and we
have yet to get used to it it has a
consequence that feels really
unintuitive
in a positive sum world it's in your
personal selfish best interest that
every human on planet earth is well off
it's good for you if people in obscure
parts of countries you've never heard of
are prospering
there is a genuine selfish argument for
making the world a better place
in a positive some world the more people
are well off the better your own life is
this is because of the nature of
innovation it is fundamentally driven by
supply and demand
the supply increases when more people
have the freedom and education to
contribute
they become inventors researchers
engineers or thinkers that come up with
new ideas
the demand for ideas increases as people
get richer and can pay for new solutions
they increase the size of the market for
innovations innovation follows
incentives
so naturally if many people want and can
pay for something it will get the
innovators attention and energy
improving the lives of those who are
worst off has a multiplying effect it
increases demand for ideas while at the
same time making it easier for ideas to
be produced
let's take an example that interests all
of us a cure for cancer
if there are 1 billion people in the
world that have the wealth to pay for
cancer treatments innovation will follow
this demand
so hundreds of billions of dollars have
been invested in medical research
this had a huge effect but we're still
nowhere near to curing all forms of
cancer
today every sixth person in the world
dies of cancer and you might be one of
them
now imagine if demand were higher
imagine instead of one billion people
being able to pay for a cure for cancer
there were four billion or seven billion
imagine how far medicine could have
developed if we'd invested seven times
as much in curing cancer
on top of that there's so much human
potential being wasted right now
the work of a poor farmer in a
developing nation is not useful to you
but if he becomes better off his
children might spend their time in
university developing things that are
useful to you
instead of having some hot spots of
innovation in the developed world we
would have many hot spots all over the
world
the research output of humanity would be
many times what it is right now
could we have cured cancer by now if
that were the case well maybe if we
spent seven times as much on research
had seven times as many people working
on it and a global network of medical
research things would certainly be
further ahead than they are now
and this is the core of the argument the
more people want the same thing that you
want the more likely you are to get it
that is what it means to live in a
positive sun world
you don't gain more pie if poor places
stay poor instead you get more pie if
poor places get richer contribute ideas
and grow the global pie do you like
space travel
imagine there were billions of people in
africa and asia with their own space
programs and demand for satellites and
moon bases and cities on mars
do you like being alive a few billion
people paying for medical research could
literally save your life
it's in your interest for people around
the world to become better off
the faster we get to this version of the
world the better for you personally
no matter what your motivation is
working on a better world is a very good
thing to do
for others
and for you
this video was a collaboration with max
rosa and our world in data and supported
by the bill and melinda gates foundation
if you want to help us stay afloat and
make more videos you can support us on
patreon or get some of our fancy posters