welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy agents of
pollination agents of pollination are
the various living organisms and abiotic
factors that Aid in the transfer of
pollen from the male reproductive organs
or the antlers of a flower to the female
reproductive organs or the stigma of the
same or another
flower this transfer allows for
fertilization and the production of
seeds these agents play an important
role in the reproductive cycle of
flowering
plants what is
pollen pollen is a dust likee substance
that flowers make it is made up of small
grains that contain the male cells
needed for the fertilization process in
plant
reproduction what is
pollination pollination is the transfer
of pollen this dust-like substance from
one part of a flow to another part of
the same flow or from one flower to a
different flower through this process
plants are able to make seeds and grow
more of themselves in other words
pollination is the process by which
plants reproduce
some plants depend on external factors
to
reproduce those external factors might
include
pollinators what is a
pollinator a pollinator is an organism
or abiotic factor that helps to move
pollen
around when animals called pollinators
visit flowers in search of food tiny
specks of pollen become attached to
their bodies as they move from flour to
flower they will leave the pollen from
one flower onto a different flower when
this occurs fertilization might happen
and the flowers may make seeds that have
the potential to grow into new
plants pollinators act as Nature's
delivery service bringing pollen from
one flower to another here are some
examples of living organisms that act as
pollinators bees they are one of the
most well-known
pollinators bees visit flowers to
collect nectar and pollen and as they
move from flower to flower they help
pollinate them
butterflies these colorful insects also
help pollinate flowers as they sip
nectar from them their long tongs known
as prases works like a straw and are
perfect for reaching deep into
flowers
hummingbirds these time tiny birds have
long beaks and tongues that are perfect
for reaching nectar in flowers as they
drink nectar they accidentally pick up
and transfer pollen beetles some beetles
like ladybugs also help pollinate
flowers they crawl around on flowers
looking for food and in the process they
transfer pollen
moths like butterflies moths are
attracted to flowers at night they help
pollinate certain flowers as they feed
on
nectar Birds besides hummingbirds other
birds like Sunbirds and some species of
sparrows also act as pollinators when
they visit flowers in search of
Nector bats in some parts of the world
bats play a crucial role in pollination
especially of night blooming flowers
they drink nectar and inadvertently
trans for pollen between
flowers these are just a few of the
animals that Aid in the pollination of
flowers other agents of pollination
include wind water and human
activity wind can move the pollen grains
from one flower to
another this is also true for water
aquatic plants often rely on water to
move pollen grains
around in the case of agricultural
settings humans can also serve as agents
of pollination by manually transferring
pollen between flowers a process known
as artificial pollination or hand
pollination agents of pollination play a
vital role in the transfer of pollen
thereby enabling the fertilization
process in flowering
plants they are important not only to
the reproduction of plants but to
biodiversity the stabilization of
ecosystems and they aid in food
production additionally agents of
pollination have economic effects on
crop production and the overall beauty
of various
habitats protecting and conserving
pollinators is essential for maintaining
biodiversity food security and
environmental sustain ability I hope you
learned something about the Agents of
pollination today thanks for taking this
Learning Journey with me until next time
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email EA
Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel
[Music]
but