AI can literally lend you a hand but
hands are complicated if your hand were
a video game character you'd need 27
buttons to control it millions of
possible button combinations need to be
translated to a robotic hand in real
time with as little delay as possible so
for the past 60 years researchers have
basically been working through one
combination at a time AI comes in handy
by speeding up the process learning the
move set from a healthy hand and
adapting it to a robotic hand is much
faster now so how does it work what you
need is one healthy hand to wear a data
glove and a microchip riddled with a
bunch of electrical sensors in your
residual limb many of the movements of
your hand are made in tandem with
muscles in the rest of your arm when you
try to move your missing hand the
sensors on the chip read these movements
and send them to a machine learning
algorithm after an initial training
phase it can translate these signals
into moving a robotic hand that's
connected via Bluetooth and just like
that