[Music]
rogue planets are planets that travel
through the universe alone they inhabit
the dark and vast space between the
Stars drifting alone through Eternal
darkness no light warms their surfaces
and they're exposed to the freezing cold
of outer space they know no Seasons no
days and no nights which could give away
the passing of time and yet Rog planets
might carry alien life to all corners of
the Galaxy how would that work and how
does a planet become a rogue
[Music]
anyway there are several very different
things that get called rogue planets for
example sub Brown dwarfs gas giants that
form from collapsing gas clouds and the
boring little brothers of brown dwarves
they're a sort of failed star and we'll
now stop talking about them
a far more interesting sort of Rogue are
terrestrial planets similar to Earth
that got kicked out of their planetary
system Young Star systems are dangerous
places where protoplanets are battling
for the available Mass guzzling up as
much material as possible in this fight
for dominance they collide with each
other or get dangerously close to each
other's orbits if a very massive Planet
moves its orbit closer to the star it
can kick smaller planets out of the
system but just because a planet has
survived The Growing Pains of formation
doesn't mean it's safe planetary systems
can be disrupted by flybys from stars or
black holes at any point up to half of
all planets born could end up as Rogues
scientists don't agree on the numbers
but it's likely that at the very least
there are billions of rogue planets in
the Milky Way alone most Rogues will
share the same depressing fate as their
star becomes smaller day by day the
planet's surface quickly cools down to-
27 20°
C if they have oceans they'll freeze and
become as hard as Bedrock their
atmospheres will sink down to the
surface and eventually freeze too but
weirdly enough some of these Frozen dark
deserts could Harbor
life to understand how let's imagine a
planet similar to Earth in the same
order of magnitude in terms of mass and
composition if we put it into deep space
how could it still support life
as far as we understand the nature of
Life there is one indispensable
ingredient it needs liquid water water
is important because it mixes things
both matter and energy which lets
interesting chemistry happen like life
so our planet needs enough energy to
keep at least a part of our oceans warm
enough to sustain liquid water
annoyingly about
99.97% of Earth's energy budget comes
from the Sun so our imaginary Rogue
Earth needs to work with the
0.03% of energy it has left which almost
exclusively comes from its hot Center
Earth's inner core is a giant metal ball
about as hot as the surface of the Sun
that's surrounded by the outer core made
up of liquid metals that are very very
slowly solidifying releasing a lot of
heat in the process as long as this
process is ongoing our planet will be
geologically active with solid and
liquid material moving around and
transporting energy to the surface where
it can be harnessed as geothermal energy
while the hot core of every planet will
cool off eventually this process takes
billions of years enough time for life
to come into existence and
Thrive there's even one scenario that
could allow an earthlike planet to have
oceans that are not frozen over if the
planet had an extremely dense and High
Press hydrogen atmosphere the gas would
not freeze and could trap enough of the
heat trying to escape the planet to
enable oceans that extend all the way to
the surface and there's another possible
way to stay warm moons if a rope Planet
brings a moon or more along with them a
large enough Moon could inject
additional energy into the system via
tidal forces these forces stretch and
squeeze the planet a little bit every
day like kneading dough keeping it warm
but the most likely scenario for a rogue
bearing life is one with subglacial
oceans under a kilometer thick layer of
mostly water I these are not completely
absurd since we already have a few of
them in the solar system so how could
life sustain itself at the bottom of a
completely dark cold ocean on earth deep
down in our oceans in complete darkness
in volcanically active areas there are
hydrothermal vents called black smokers
they spew out a cloud of black material
and hot water providing a constant flow
of minerals from Earth's mantle bacteria
feed on the minerals and produce organic
materials which attracts crustations B
valves snails fish octopus and Tube
worms up to 2 m long not only are
hydrothermal vents home to an incredibly
diverse group of living beings but also
a contender for the place where life
could have begun on Earth billions of
years ago in the dark ocean of a rogue
planet similar vents or volcanic
activity could be the starting point and
basis for complex ecosystems we can only
imagine right now one upside an
ecosystem in a rogue Planet ocean has is
that the environment is extremely stable
the thick ice sheet protects it from all
sorts of Extinction events and as long
as the energy from the core keeps on
coming things stay pretty much the same
the most likely forms of life are
bacteria and other microorganisms but
given enough time more complex alien
animals could feed on the smaller beings
and Thrive it's not impossible that
intelligent life could emerge in such an
environment if it did it would find
itself in a pretty weird world
constricted by an impossible wall of
rock hard ice at the top and bedrock at
the bottom without any plants to store
Star Energy there would be no wood oil
or coal even if there were it's not like
youd discover fire at the bottom of an
ocean without this energy Metals may
never be forged into useful
things our intelligent alien friends
might never break through the ice they
might never realize that there is such a
thing as outside and assume that their
small world is all there is millions of
generations might live and die in these
dark oceans ignorant of the unbelievably
Big Universe above the ice until the
core of their Planet cools off and all
life vanishes as the oceans completely
freeze the remnants of cultures and
ecosystems will be trapped in an icy
grave forever if you think about it it
might be better not to be aware of all
that but the concept is disturbing and
exciting the universe might be teaming
with life trapped on planets that are
basically impossible to leave
worlds like this could frequently pass
the solar system without us even
knowing maybe one day in the far future
humans will set foot on one of these
Frozen worlds and try to say hello