welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy let's learn about cells all
living creatures are made up of
microscopic Parts called cells cells are
the building blocks for all life and are
the smallest known unit of life that can
replicate
independently living organisms can be
made up of one or more cells single
celled organisms are called
unicellular while organisms with two or
more cells are called
multicellular there are many types of
cells each with their own unique
structure and function the two main
types include proc cryotic cells these
are simple cells without a nucleus like
bacteria UK cryotic cells these are more
complex cells with a nucleus like the
ones in plants and
animals every living thing is made up of
cells and these cells work together to
help the organism grow move and stay
healthy in this video we will take a
closer look at ukic cells more
specifically plant and animal cells
cells are made up of organel which are
tiny parts inside the cell that do
specific jobs much like organs in our
bodies both plant and animal cells have
a cell membrane this is like a thin
protective wall around the cell it keeps
everything inside safe and lets good
things in while keeping bad things out
unlike animal cells plant cells also
have a cell wall a cell wall is a strong
rigid layer that surrounds the cell
membrane it provides structural support
and protection
helping the cell maintain its shape the
cell wall is mainly made of cellulose a
type of
carbohydrate the cell wall also helps
regulate what enters and exits the cell
inside the cell there is a jellylike
fluid that fills it up this is where the
cell's activities happen this is known
as the
cytoplasm this is the nucleus it is the
cell's control center like the brain of
the cell it holds the instructions or
DNA for everything the cell
does here are the
mitochondria these are the powerhouses
that give the cell
energy here is another organel called
the vacu in animal cells this is usually
referred to as
vesicles it functions mainly in storage
of neutri nutrients waste products and
other materials the cell might need in
plant cells it also works to support the
structure of the plant vaces are
generally larger in plant cells often
occupying most of the cells
interior plant cells differ from animal
cells in that they contain chloroplast
it is the site within the plant where
photosynthesis takes place which is a
process that converts sunlight carbon
dioxide and water into sugars and oxygen
chloroplasts contain a green pigment
called chlorophyll which captures light
energy this energy is then used to
produce food for the plant making
chloroplasts essential for the plant's
growth and energy Supply cells also
contain Bui apparatus these organel
package and ship out things the cells
make ribosome
these are tiny machines that make
proteins which are super important for
the cell endoplasmic reticulum often
called ER helps make and move proteins
and other important things the cells
need cells are the basic building blocks
of all living organisms performing
essential functions to sustain life they
regulate internal processes convert
nutrients into energy and elim eliminate
waste cells contain specialized
structures which coordinate activities
like growth reproduction and
Metabolism in multicellular organisms
cells work together to form tissues and
organs enabling complex biological
functions their ability to replicate and
respond to the environment is crucial
for the survival and adaptation of
living
[Music]
beings I hope you learned something
about sales today thanks for taking this
Learning Journey with me until next
[Music]
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
EA Homeschool Academy
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel
[Music]