welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy all about rocks and
minerals what is a
rock a rock is a solid natural substance
that is made up of minerals and other
organic materials that are formed over
time there are three main
classifications for rocks and they are
grouped based on their
formation the three basic types of rocks
are
Ignus
sedimentary and metamorphic
[Music]
rocks the word Ignus comes from the
Latin word ignis which translates to the
word
fire so Ignus rocks are formed when the
molten magma from volcanoes come to the
surface and
solidifies here are some examples of ous
rocks Granite this is a coar grained ous
rock made up mainly of quartz belt bar
and
micia granite is often used in
construction
Basalt this is a fine grained dark
colored ous rock that forms quickly from
rapidly cooling
lava obsidian this this is a dark glassy
ous rock that forms when magma cools
very quickly it has a smooth reflective
surface sedimentary rocks are formed as
the name suggests from
sediments sediments are smaller pieces
of objects like minerals pieces of
plants or other organic
material the sediments are subjected to
immense levels of pressure over time
that creates the
Rocks here are some examples of
sedimentary
rocks
sandstone this is a sedimentary rock
composed mainly of sand sized minerals
rocks or other organic
materials it appears in a variety of
colors including tan brown red or white
it has a grainy
texture
Limestone this is a sedimentary rock
composed mainly of the mineral calite it
is usually formed in Marine environments
from shells coral and other organic
material its texture and color may
vary
Shale this is a sedimentary rock that is
composed of mainly clay materials it may
appear in colors like dark gray or black
it is very fragile and can split easily
into
layers it is formed when mud and Clay
are exposed to immense
pressure metamorphic rocks are formed
when Ignus and sedimentary rocks are
exposed to high temperatures and high
pressures these circumstances cause the
rocks to move morph or change into a new
type of rock called a metamorphic
rock here are some examples of
metamorphic rocks
marble this is a rock that forms when
limestone is exposed to extreme
temperatures and
pressure it usually presents with a
smooth polished
appearance slate this metamorphic rock
is formed when shaped tail or mudstone
is exposed to immense heat and pressure
it has a distinct ability to break into
thin layers or flat
sheets quart site this is a metamorphic
rock that is formed when Sandstone is
exposed to extreme temperatures and
pressures it usually has a granular or
sugary
texture now that we know the three main
classification for rocks let's learn a
bit more about
minerals what is a
mineral minerals are inorganic solid
substances that have specific chemical
compositions minerals are the building
blocks for
rocks they have specific properties like
cluster shape hardness and
color here are some examples of of
minerals
quartz this is a common mineral that is
found in various types of rocks it can
appear in white pink or purple fed Spar
this is a group of minerals that are
abundant in the Earth's crust they can
appear as white pink or green
calite this is a mineral that appears in
a variety of colors including green
white blue and
orange this is a very soft
mineral rocks and minerals have various
uses in our daily lives some examples
include the construction of houses and
roadways jewelry making and
agriculture additionally rocks and
minerals are also used in art and
decoration there are many more uses or
applications for rocks and minerals in
our world but the best places to observe
them is in their natural
environments now we know that rocks are
formed from minerals and both are part
of nature we also know that there are
three main classifications for rocks ous
sedimentary and
metamorphic I hope you learned something
about rocks and minerals today thanks
for taking this Learning Journey with me
until next
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
eah Homeschool Academy
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel