welcome to eza homeschool academy
life cycle of ants
ants
one of nature's strongest creatures are
truly remarkable
there are over 12 000 species of ants
and some are said to be able to lift 20
times their own body weight that's like
a seven-year-old lived in a car
[Music]
ants are invertebrates because they do
not have a backbone
they belong to the insect group
[Music]
most ant species are omnivorous
which means they eat both plant and
animal matter
[Music]
let's take a look at the parts of an ant
an ant has a head
with two antennae on top
a thorax
an abdomen
and six legs
[Music]
ants can be found on every continent
except antarctica
because it is too cold
[Music]
these marvelous creatures live in social
groups called colonies
some of nature's most expert architects
ants
built their colonies in a variety of
places
some built their colonies underground
some in trees
under rocks
in forest litter
and even in rotting wood
they are versatile and adaptable
ant colonies are amazing
for those species that tunnel
underground they build very intricate
structures
beneath the surface of the mound are
numerous tunnels that connect rooms or
chambers each with their own purpose
there are chambers for food storage and
there are chambers that serve as
nurseries for juvenile ants
furthermore some of the chambers are
used by the adult workers as a resting
room
[Music]
there are three main types of ants in a
colony
the queen
the males
and the female workers
both the male ants and the queen have
wings
the queen sheds her wings when she is
ready to nest and lay eggs
[Music]
as her name suggests the queen is the
leader of the colony
her sole job is to lay thousands of eggs
to prolong the life of the colony
depending on the species
some queen ants can live up to 30 years
some ant colonies will have multiple
queens
[Music]
the male ants or drones have one purpose
in the colony
their job is to mate with the queen so
that she can continue to lay eggs
drones usually die soon after mating
with the queen
the most abundantly occurring ants in
the colony
are female workers
likely if you have ever seen an ant it
was a female as they are responsible for
foraging for food
building up the nest
caring for the young and protecting the
colony
let's take a look at the life cycle of
an ant
[Music]
ants grow through a four-stage process
known as a complete metamorphosis
the life of an ant starts in an egg
and eggs are small
soft and oval shaped
from the eggs the ant larva will emerge
and larvae have no eyes or legs
they eat a lot so they rely on the adult
caretakers to provide food constantly
they grow rapidly and molt as they get
bigger
[Music]
once the larva is ready to transition to
the next phase of life it will form a
cocoon made of silk around its body
the larva usually makes its cocoon near
a solid surface like the wall of the
nest
while inside the cocoon all the cells of
the body will be completely transformed
into the adult ant
[Music]
the final stage of the ants
metamorphosis is complete when the adult
ant emerges from its cocoon
the entire life cycle of most ant
species
is usually between 6 and 10 weeks
[Music]
let's review
like most insects
ants undergo a complete metamorphosis
as they progress through their various
stages of life
they hatch from an egg to the larval
stage then build a cocoon in the pupa
stage before finally emerging as an
adult
[Music]
did you know that ants do not have ears
they communicate with each other using
various scents called pheromones as well
as through vibrations in the ground
and they experience this through their
feet
[Music]
time for another fun fact
ants do not have lungs yet they breathe
they breathe air in and out through tiny
holes in their bodies
ants have been around for many years
these fascinating creatures continue to
intrigue researchers and scientists
alike
ants are highly adaptable
and like all creatures play a vital role
in their natural ecosystem
the next time you get annoyed at a group
of ants for crashing your outdoor meal
time
just know they're working hard to
maintain
and sustain their colony
thanks for learning with me today
[Music]
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email easy a homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel