GMOs are one of the most controversial
areas of science genetic engineering is
used in many fields but even though
medical applications like GM insulin are
widely accepted the debate heats up when
it comes to food and agriculture why is
that why is the same thing treated so
differently let's try to get to the
bottom of this and explore the facts the
fears and the future of
GMOs
[Music]
humans have been genetically modifying
plants and animals for thousands of
years maybe a few of your crops had very
good yields maybe one of your wolves was
especially loyal so you did the smart
thing and bred the plants and animals
that had traits beneficial to you traits
are just an expression of genes
so with each generation those genes got
more
pronounced after thousands of years
almost every single plant and animal
around us is vastly different from its
pre-domestication
state if humans have been changing genes
for Millennia what makes a so-called
genetically modified organism or GMO
different selective breeding is
basically hoping for Lucky hits genetic
engineering eliminates this Factor we
can choose the traits we want make fruit
fruit grow bigger immune to pests and so
on so why are people concerned about
[Music]
them let's start with one of the most
common objections to GMOs gene flow
meaning GM crops could mix with
traditional crops and introduce unwanted
new characteristics into them there is a
method that might guarantee complete
prevention but is a big anti-gmo
argument by itself Terminator seeds
the idea is that they could produce
sterile plants requiring Farmers to buy
new seeds every year the very concept of
this however caused a public outcry
stopping the technology being put to
use this brings us back to the
unintentional spreading of engineered
DNA there have been cases of GMOs
growing where they weren't planted and
traces of modified genes found in
foreign
crops but GM plants can't run wild
entirely many crops poate themselves and
all crops have to be related to mingle
there are also cultural methods like
buffer zones to keep unintentional
Crossing at a minimum but if it's
possible in principle that a GMO could
unintentionally cross with a non- GMO
there's actually a more important
question is food that comes from GM
crops different to food from non-gm
crops this question has been a major
concern from the very beginning GM
plants that are destined to be eaten are
checked for possible dangers and the the
results are evaluated by multiple
agencies after more than 30 years and
thousands of studies the science is in
Eating GMO plants is no more risky than
their non- GMO equivalent but don't just
take our word for it sources for this
and other claims are in the video
description but what about plants that
have been engineered to be toxic for
example BT crops a gene borrowed from
the bacterium bacillus thuringensis lets
engineered plants produce a protein that
destroys the Digest system of specific
insect pests the plant makes its own
pesticide insects that eat it
die that sounds alarming pesticide
sprays can be washed off while the
poison in BT crops is inside the plant
but actually it's not a big deal poison
is really just a question of different
perspectives what's harmless to one
species might kill another coffee for
example is a poison that kills insects
but is harmless to us or take chocolate
it's dangerous for dogs but a pleasure
for
humans BT crops produce a protein that
is tailored to the specific design of
the digestive tract of certain insects
it's completely harmless for us there's
also the opposite approach plants that
are engineered to be resistant to
certain weed killers this way farmers
can use them widely killing the other
plants competing for resources without
harming the crop here we get to the dark
underbelly of GMOs for the pesticide
industry they are big business over 90%
of all cash crops in the US are
herbicide resistant mostly to glyphosate
as a result the use of glyphosate has
increased greatly that isn't only bad
glyphosate is much less harmful to
humans than many other
herbicides still this means Farmers have
a strong incentive to rely on this one
method only casting more balanced ways
of managing weeds asight that's one of
the most fundamental problems with the
GMO debate much of the criticism M of
this technology is actually criticism of
modern Agriculture and the business
practice of the huge corporations that
control our food supply this criticism
is not only valid it's also important we
need to change agriculture to a more
sustainable model GMOs as a technology
are actually an ally and not an enemy in
that fight helping to save and protect
nature and minimize our impact on the
environment
let's look at some positive examples
eggplant is an important crop in
Bangladesh but often whole harvests are
destroyed by pests Farmers had to rely
heavily on pesticides Not only was this
very expensive Farmers also frequently
got sick the introduction of a new GM
eggplant in 2013 stopped this the same
BT protein we talked about before an
effective killer of insects but harmless
to humans was engineered into them this
reduced insecticide use on eggplants by
more than 80% the health of farmers
improved and their income Rose
dramatically and sometimes a GM approach
is the only option in the 1990s the
papaya industry in Hawaii was under
attack from the ringspot virus which
threatened to wout Hawaiian papaya the
solution was a papaya genetically
modified to be vaccinated against the
virus without it the state's papaya
industry would have
collapsed
all these stories show a very narrow
application 99% of all GMOs we use right
now produce pesticides or are resistant
against them there is so much more we
could do scientists are working on GMOs
that could improve our diet plants that
produce more or different nutrients like
fruit with higher antioxidant levels
that help to fight diseases or rice with
additional vitamins on a larger scale
we're trying to engineer plants that are
more resilient to CL change plants that
can better adapt to erratic weather and
adverse soil conditions making them
resistant to droughts or
floods GMOs could also not only reduce
agriculture's impact on the environment
but actively help to protect it
scientists are working on crops that can
draw nitrogen from the air like microbes
nitrogen is a common fertilizer but its
buildup pollutes the groundwater and
speeds up climate
change plants that collect their own
nitrogen could fix two problems at once
the overuse of fertilizers in the
developed world as well as the shortage
of it in developing countries we could
even modify plants to become super
effective carbon collectors like the
American chestnut tree to mitigate and
actually reverse climate change with the
tools we have today our imagination is
the
[Music]
limit the world eats 11 million pounds
of food every day a un estimate suggests
we'll need 70% more by
2050 we could grow that food by clearing
more and more Forest to create fields
and pastures and by using more
pesticides or we find a way to do it on
the land we've got right now with more
effective methods like GM crops
intensifying farming instead of
expanding it means GMOs could become the
new organic in a nutshell GMOs have the
potential to not only drastically change
agriculture but to also dampen the
effects of our own irresponsible
Behavior
GMOs could be our most powerful weapon
to save our
biosphere this video took more than 600
hours to make which would be impossible
without viewer support on patreon.com if
you'd like to support carefully
researched content made with love it's
really very helpful and you can get your
own bird as a reward if you want to
learn more about genetic modification we
have more videos explaining the
opportunities and risks of the
technology and how it could impact our
future