welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy today we will learn about
avalanches what is an
avalanche an avalanche is a natural
occurrence it describes the movement of
large amounts of snow down a slope or
mountain when this happens the snow
moving down the mountain can potentially
destroy everything in its
[Music]
path what causes an
avalanche Avalanches are caused by a
variety of
factors Avalanches are more likely to
occur on a steep mountain or slope that
is covered with snow and that has very
little
vegetation since there are not many
trees to hold snow in place it is likely
to slide away under the right conditions
a weak layer of snow within the snow
cover can also lead to an
avalanche as snow falls it will form
layers if there is a layer that has
melted and be frozen it may become
slick when new snow falls on top of this
slick layer it may become unstable and
lead to an
avalanche Avalanches occur when they're
triggered when
warming temperatures rain snow or
earthquakes can trigger them
naturally hikers skiers vibrations from
heavy machinery and snowmobiles can also
trigger an
aalan when and where do avalanches occur
an avalanche is most likely to occur
immediately after a snowstorm if there
is a Surface bed of snow on top of a a
steep slope and a weaker layer of snow
under snow cap they are more prevalent
in the winter months in the northern
hemisphere which are between December
and April they can occur however at any
time during the year as long as the
conditions are
present consequences of an avalanche
depending on the strength of an
avalanche the consequences can be quite
devastating the movement of the snow and
debris down the mountain can threaten
the life of all living things in the
path people livestock vegetation and
anything in its path can potentially be
affected property like homes fences
roads or other structures can be damaged
or destroyed during an avalanche
furthermore Transportation Systems can
be disrupted as snow and debris from an
avalanche can cover rails and block
roads Avalanches can also disrupt
communication systems as they may bring
down power lines and other utilities
which can affect people living in and
around the
area what can be done to prevent an
avalanche Avalanches are natural
occurrences and therefore they cannot be
entirely
prevented knowing how an avalanche can
affect the environment and understanding
their impact is one way to stay safe
should an avalanche occur in your
area people living in an areas that are
prone to Avalanches often erect fences
and other structures in an effort to
control where the snow and debris will
flow explosives are sometimes used to
trigger smaller avalanches in an effort
to prevent a larger catastrophic
occurrence people living in around areas
that are prone to Avalanches are
encourag to stay off the slopes and
roadways directly following a major
snowstorm if traveling be sure to do so
in groups take an avalanche safety
course if you are planning to go skiing
hiking or participating in other
recreational activities in snow covered
regions also be sure to have emergency
evacuation plans and other supplies on
hand should they become
[Music]
necessary Avalanches are primarily
naturally occurring events they happen
on snow covered mountains with very
little vegetation to hold the snow in
place warming temperatures and other
factors can cause snow to slip down the
mountain which can destroy life and
property in its path on its
descent being aware of their causes and
effects on the environment is one way to
be prepared in the event of an avalanche
happening in your
area I hope you learned something about
avalanches today thank you for taking
this Learning Journey with me until next
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
EA Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our
Channel