the international banking system is an
enigma
there are more than 30 000 different
banks worldwide and they hold
unbelievable amounts of assets the top
10 banks alone account for roughly 25
trillion us dollars today banking can
seem very complex but originally the
idea was to make life simpler
[Music]
11th century italy was the center of
european trading merchants from all over
the continent met to trade their goods
but there was one problem too many
currencies in circulation in pisa
merchants had to deal with seven
different types of coins and had to
exchange their money constantly
this exchange business which commonly
took place outdoors on benches is where
we get the word bank from from the word
bankl italian for bench the dangers of
travelling counterfeit money and the
difficulty of getting a loan got people
thinking it was time for a new business
model horn brokers started to give
credit to businessmen while genoese
merchants developed cashless payments
networks of banks spread all over europe
handing out credit even to the church or
european kings what about today in a
nutshell banks are in the risk
management business
this is a simplified version of the way
it works people keep their money in
banks and receive a small amount of
interest the bank takes this money and
lends it out at much higher interest
rates it's a calculated risk because
some of the lenders will default on
their credit this process is essential
for our economic system because it
provides resources for people to buy
things like houses or for industry to
expand their businesses and grow so
banks take funds that are unused by
savers and turn them into funds society
can use to do stuff other sources of
income for banks include accepting
saving deposits the credit card business
buying and selling currencies custodian
business and cash management services
the main problem with banks nowadays is
that a lot of them have abandoned their
traditional role as providers of
long-term financial products in favor of
short-term gains that carry much higher
risks during the financial boom most
major banks adopted financial constructs
that were barely comprehensible and did
their own trading in a bid to make fast
money and earn their executives and
traders millions in bonuses this was
nothing short of gambling and damaged
whole economies and societies like back
in 2008 when banks like lehman brothers
gave credit to basically anyone who
wanted to buy a house and thereby put
the bank in an extremely dangerous risk
position this led to the collapse of the
housing market in the us and parts of
europe causing stock prices to plummet
which eventually led to a global banking
crisis and one of the largest financial
crises in history hundreds of billions
of dollars just evaporated millions of
people lost their jobs and lots of money
most of the world's major banks had to
pay billions in fines and bankers became
some of the least trusted professionals
the us government and the european union
had to put together huge bailout
packages to purchase bad assets and stop
the banks from going bankrupt new
regulations were put into force to
govern the banking business compulsory
bank emergency funds were enforced to
absorb shocks in the event of another
financial crisis but other pieces of
tough new legislation were successfully
blocked by the banking lobby today other
models of providing financing are
gaining ground fast like new investment
banks that charge a yearly fee and do
not get commissions on sales thus
providing the motivation to act in the
best interests of their clients or
credit unions cooperative initiatives
that were established in the 19th
century to circumvent credit sharks in a
nutshell they provide the same financial
services as banks but focus on shared
value rather than profit maximization
the self-proclaimed goal is to help
members create opportunities like
starting small businesses expanding
farms or building family homes while
investing back into communities they are
controlled by their members who also
elect the board of directors
democratically worldwide credit union
systems vary significantly ranging from
a handful of members to organizations
worth several billion us dollars and
hundreds of thousands of members the
focus on benefits for their members
impacts the risk credit unions are
willing to take which explains why
credit unions although also hurting
survived the last financial crisis way
better than traditional banks
not to forget the explosion of
crowdfunding in recent years aside from
making awesome video games possible
platforms are rows that enable people to
get loans from large groups of small
investors circumventing the bank as a
middleman but it also works for industry
lots of new technology companies started
out on kickstarter or indiegogo the
funding individual gets the satisfaction
of being part of a bigger thing and can
invest in ideas they believe in while
spreading the risk so widely that if the
project fails the damage is limited and
last but not least micro credits lots of
very small loans mostly handed out in
developing countries that help people
escape poverty people who were
previously unable to get access to the
money they needed to start a business
because they weren't deemed worth the
time
nowadays the granting of micro credits
has evolved into a multi-billion dollar
business so banking might not be up your
street but the bank's role of providing
funds to people and businesses is
crucial for our society and has to be
done who will do it and how it will be
done in the future is up for us to
decide though
[Music]
you