Welcome to Easa Homeschool
Academy. Welcome to the Big Idea series.
The series where we answer curious
questions for curious minds. Today's big
idea question is why do we need bees?
These tiny pollinators have a massive
impact on our food, our ecosystems, and
our future.
Bees are nature's most effective
pollinators. When bees visit a flower to
gather nectar, grains of pollen stick to
their bodies. As they move to the next
flower, some of that pollen is
transferred, fertilizing the
plant. This simple process is
responsible for the growth of seeds,
fruit, and more flowers.
Without pollination, many plants
wouldn't be able to reproduce. There are
over 20,000 species of bees. And while
honeybees get most of the attention,
wild bees like bumblebees, carpenter
bees, and solitary bees are also
essential to
pollination. Some species are so
specialized they only pollinate certain
plants. Globally, about 75% of flowering
plant species depend on animal
pollinators, including bees. And when it
comes to human agriculture, about 1/3 of
all the food we eat relies on
pollinators in some way. Fruits like
apples, strawberries, melons, and
avocados depend on bee pollination.
So do nuts like almonds and vegetables
like pumpkins and
squash. In fact, almond trees are
entirely dependent on honeybees for
pollination. In California, thousands of
beekeepers transport their hives each
spring to support the state's almond
orchids, one of the largest pollination
areas in the world. Even crops that
don't require pollination like wheat or
corn benefit
indirectly. Bees support cover crops,
soil health, and livestock forage such
as alalfa and clover, which are
essential to animal farming. Bees don't
just help feed humans.
Pollination supports the growth of
plants that feed birds, deer, insects,
and countless other animals in the food
chain. Bees play a central role in
maintaining
biodiversity. As pollinators, they
support the health of wild plant
communities, which provide habitats and
food for countless species.
When pollination breaks down, plants
fail to produce fruit or seeds. This
impacts the species that rely on them,
from butterflies to
bears. In some regions, the loss of wild
bees has led to noticeable drops in the
population of fruitbearing shrubs and
trees. Pollination also affects the
structure of entire ecosystems.
Diverse pollinated plant life helps
prevent soil erosion, improves water
retention, and supports carbon storage.
All crucial for climate resilience. Bees
make a significant contribution to the
global
economy. The estimated value of
pollination services is around 2,000 to
6,000 billion per year worldwide.
In the United States alone, honeybees
increase crop values by over$15 billion
dollar annually. Crops like blueberries,
watermelons, and cucumbers produce more
and higher quality fruit when bees are
involved. Beekeeping also supports jobs
in agriculture, trade, science, and
education.
From rural farms to urban rooftop hives,
bees are connected to human livelihoods.
Despite their importance, bee
populations are under threat. Multiple
stressors are causing sharp declines in
both wild and managed bee species. One
major threat is habitat
loss. Urban expansion and monoculture
farming reduce the diversity of flowers
bees need to survive.
Pesticides can harm bee navigation and
immunity. Parasites can devastate entire
colonies. Beekeepers report higher than
average winter losses each year. In some
areas, bee populations have dropped by
over
50%. Fortunately, there are many ways to
support bees. Planting pollinator
friendly gardens with native wild
flowers provides food and
habitat. Avoiding or reducing pesticide
use protects their
health. Supporting organic and
regenerative farms which prioritize
pollinator safety helps create better
agricultural systems. You can also buy
local honey, support beekeeping
organizations, and even host bee hotels
for wild solitary bees. Every effort
counts toward rebuilding pollinator
populations. Bees are small, but their
impact is enormous. From food to forest,
they hold together the systems that we
all depend on. Thanks for joining us on
Big Ideas. Join us next time as we
answer another curious
question. As always, thank you for
watching. Tell us what you want to see
next. Email easy
homeschoolacademy@yahoo.com. Like and
share our videos. Please subscribe to
our channel.