Welcome to Easa Homeschool
Academy. Welcome to the Big Idea series,
where we answer curious questions for
curious minds. Do animals use
tools? Exploring nature's smartest
problem solvers. When we think of using
tools, we often imagine humans building
machines or crafting with precision.
But humans aren't the only species that
shape and use the world around them.
Across oceans, forests, and savas, many
animals have developed their own use of
tools. In this video, we'll explore how
five incredible animals. Sea otterters,
chimpanzees, elephants, orangutans, and
octopuses use tools to survive, thrive,
and even teach one another. Sea
otterters, often seen floating on their
backs in the ocean, are much more than
just
adorable. They're among the few marine
mammals known to use tools.
Sea otterters commonly use rocks as
anvils to crack open tough shelled prey
like clams, muscles, and sea
urchins. What's fascinating is that some
utters have been observed selecting a
preferred rock and carrying it with them
in a loose skin pouch under their arms,
a kind of natural tool belt. Researchers
have found that tool use in sea
otterters varies by region and may be
passed from mother to pup. This suggests
that sea otterters like humans have
culture behaviors that are learned and
shared socially. Another surprising
fact, by cracking open sea urchins,
otter help maintain the health of kelp
forests. Without them, sea urchin
populations would explode, devouring the
kelp and disrupting entire marine
ecosystems. Chimpanzees are some of the
most famous animal tool users, and for
good
reason. In the wild, they have been seen
using a wide range of
tools. One well-known behavior is
termite fishing.
Chimps find sticks, strip off the
leaves, and insert them into termite
mounds. Once the termites latch on, the
chimps pull the sticks out and eat their
catch. Chimpanzees also crack open hard
nuts with stones, a skill that takes
years to master.
Young chimps learn by watching their
elders, and some even go through a trial
and error learning process before
getting it right. In some regions,
chimps sharpen sticks into spears to
hunt small animals like bush babies.
This behavior adds a layer of
complexity, showing they don't just use
tools, they can modify them, too.
Elephants are renowned for their memory
and intelligence, and their tool use
reflects
that. In the wild, elephants use sticks
to scratch themselves in places they
can't reach. They also swat flies with
leafy branches, which can be seen as a
form of self-care. But elephant
ingenuity doesn't stop there.
Some have been observed using logs or
rocks to dig holes, plug water sources
to save them for later, or even create
barriers. In captivity, elephants have
been known to stack boxes or move
objects to reach food placed high above
them, demonstrating problem solving and
foresight. Perhaps most impressively,
tool use in elephants is often combined
with strong emotional
intelligence. They exhibit empathy,
mourn their dead, and show signs of
learning from one another. In the
rainforest of Borneo and
Sumatra, orangutangs display remarkable
tool use. These intelligent apes often
use sticks to pry insects out of trees
or scoop honey from
beehives. Some even use bundles of
leaves to swat bees or collect
rainwater. Researchers have recorded
orangutans making leaf gloves to handle
spiny fruits or leaf napkins to clean
themselves. In captivity, orangutans
have been observed using tools with
surprising creativity, such as using a
rake to reach food or making simple hats
out of paper or leaves. Orangutans live
mostly solitary lives, yet tool use is
still passed on from mother to
offspring. This slow-paced learning
process is part of what makes them so
fascinating.
They take their time to observe, mimic,
and refine their skills. Among
invertebrates, the octopus stands alone
in its tool using
abilities. The veined octopus, for
example, collects coconut shells and
carries them across the ocean floor.
When threatened, it assembles the halves
into a shelter, essentially a portable
home.
Octopuses also use rocks or shells to
block their dens, creating a secure
barrier. In lab experiments, they have
demonstrated problem-solving abilities
such as opening jars or navigating
mazes. What's especially intriguing is
that octopuses have neurons not just in
their brains but also in their arms,
allowing them to collect and process
information while manipulating objects
with precision. Their tool use is a
blend of intelligence, adaptability, and
sheer creativity.
From cracking shells with rocks to
building shelters out of coconuts,
animals around the world show us that
tool use isn't uniquely human. These
behaviors reflect complex thought,
cultural learning, and an ability to
adapt to challenges in their
environments. As we continue to study
these animals, we uncover just how
intelligent and resourceful the natural
world really is. Understanding their
abilities helps us appreciate the
richness of life on Earth and reminds us
that we're not the only clever ones out
there. Join us next time on Big Ideas,
where we answer curious questions for
curious minds. As always, thank you for
watching. Tell us what you want to see
next. Email easyschoolacademy@yahoo.com.
Like and share our videos. Please
subscribe to our channel.