Welcome to Easa Homeschool
Academy. Welcome to the Big Idea series,
where we answer curious questions for
curious minds. What are
primates? You may have seen monkeys at
the zoo or watched documentaries about
gorillas in the wild, but what exactly
is a primate? And did you know that
humans are primates, too? Let's explore
together. Primates are a group of
mammals that include some very familiar
animals like monkeys, apes, and yes,
people. This group also includes animals
like lemurs, lorises, and tarscers,
which you might not hear about as often.
So, what makes a primate a
primate? Let's break it down.
Primates usually have large brains
compared to the size of their bodies.
This helps them think, solve problems,
and sometimes even use
tools. They also have forward-facing
eyes, which helps them see in 3D. This
is great for climbing and jumping
through trees because they can judge
distances really well. Primates also
have grasping hands and feet with
opposable thumbs. That means their
thumbs can touch their other fingers
just like
ours. This helps them grab branches,
peel fruit, and even groom each other.
Primates are very social animals. Many
live in groups called troops, bands, or
families.
They use sounds, body language, and
facial expressions to communicate with
each other. Some, like chimpanzees, even
use tools to get food or solve
problems. For example, chimps use sticks
to catch termites. That's something not
many animals can do. Primates live in
many parts of the world, mostly in
tropical areas. You can find them in
Africa, Asia, Central and South America,
and on the islands like
Madagascar. Most primates live in trees,
especially smaller ones like tamarind
and marmicetses. Others like baboons
spend more time on the ground. Primates
have been around for a long time, about
60 million years.
Scientists think the first primates were
small tree dwelling animals that came
out mostly at
night. Over time, different types of
primates evolved. Some stayed small and
lived in trees. Others, like apes, grew
larger and developed stronger brains.
Humans are part of the great ape group.
That includes
gorillas,
chimpanzees, bonabos, and
orangutans. So, what makes humans
special if we're primates,
too? Well, humans are the only primates
that walk fully upright on two legs all
of the time.
We also have the most complex language
and we create things like art, machines,
and
cities. But when it comes to our bodies
and our DNA, we're not all that
different from other
primates. In fact, chimpanzees share
over 98% of their DNA with humans. That
means we're closer to chimps than chimps
are to monkeys.
Scientists study primates to learn more
about how humans evolved, how we behave,
and even how we care for others. Some
primates are known for showing kindness
and
teamwork. For example, bonobos are
peaceful animals that share food and
avoid fighting when they can. Watching
other primates helps us learn not only
about biology but also about emotions,
friendships, and family. Now, let's take
a closer look at the different types of
primates. There are two main groups,
streperhis and
haplorhines. Strepzerhines include
lemurs, lorises, and gallopos. They
usually have better night vision and a
strong sense of smell. Most of them are
found in Madagascar and parts of Asia
and other parts of Africa.
Haplorhines include monkeys, apes, and
humans. They usually rely more on sight
than smell and are more active during
the day. Within the monkey group, there
are two types. New world monkeys and
oldw world monkeys. New world monkeys
live in Central and South America. They
often have long tails that can wrap
around branches. These are called
prehensile tails. Examples include
spider monkeys and howler monkeys. Oldw
world monkeys live in Africa and Asia.
They don't have prehensile tails and
many of them spend time on the ground.
Baboons and macaks are good
examples. Apes are different from
monkeys. They don't have tails and
they're usually larger. Apes include
gibbons, gorillas, chimpanzees, bonobos,
orangutans, and of course, humans.
Apes are known for being especially
intelligent. They can learn sign
language, use tools, and even recognized
themselves in
mirrors. Sadly, many primates today are
in danger. Their homes are being cut
down for farming or building. Some are
hunted or captured for the pet trade.
Conservation groups are working hard to
protect primates and their habitats. We
can help too by learning more,
supporting wildlife groups, and making
choices that are better for the
environment. So, to review, primates are
a diverse, and fascinating group of
mammals. They're smart, social, and full
of personality.
From the tiny mouse lemur to the
powerful gorilla and even to us,
primates share a connection that
stretches back millions of years. Thanks
for watching the Big Idea series where
we answer curious questions for curious
minds. As always, thank you for
watching. Tell us what you want to see
next. Email eza
homeschoolacademy@yahoo.com. Like and
share our videos. Please subscribe to
our channel.