You're a chicken with bird flu now.
Spread it as fast as possible. 6 hours
after infection, your poop and saliva
become lethal weapons. Use them. Focus
on infecting chickens like you. Bred for
your meat, not a strong immune system.
Better yet, target sick birds. They're
even easier victims and can spread the
virus faster. Within 24 hours, you've
likely infected all birds who aren't
immune. Another 24 hours later, most of
your flock are dead. Brutal. But to
infect humans, you'll need a new
strategy. Only certain strains of bird
flu affect them. The deadliest by far is
H5N1. And so far, less than a thousand
humans have ever been infected. It's
time to activate your secret weapon,
pigs. They can catch both bird and human
flu, making them the perfect melting pot
to remix the viruses and cook up a
deadlier new pandemic level strain. For
bonus points, infect migrating birds.
You could even take down a few polar
bears. Wow, you're unstoppable. Just one
bird like you can wipe out millions of
others. But watch out. Beadyeyed farmers
are removing birds at the first sign of
infection and can put a stop to your
killing spree before it even starts.