black hole Stars may have been the
largest stars that ever existed they
burned brighter than galaxies and were
larger than any Star today or that could
ever exist in the future but besides
their scale what makes them special and
weird is that deep in sight they were
occupied by a cosmic parasite an
endlessly hungry black hole how is that
even possible
[Music]
black hole Stars take the weirdness of
black holes and go beyond to break
everything we know about how stars form
and grow they were only possible during
a short window of time in the early
universe but if they existed they would
solve one of the largest mysteries of
cosmology black hole stars were
excessive anywh you look at them the
most massive stars today may have about
300 solar masses a black full Star had
up to 10 million solar masses of nearly
pure
hydrogen let's take a moment to look at
what this means visually the sun weson
LL pegasi the largest star and finally
the black hole star its scale is beyond
words over 800,000 times wider than our
sun 380 times larger than the largest
star we know
today and Far Below its surface is a
black hole growing rapidly as it devours
billions upon billions of tons of matter
per
second normally Stars Are Born from
gigantic clouds collections of thousands
or millions of solar masses of mostly
hydrogen in these clouds matter starts
to accumulate around the densest spots
inside as these spots get denser their
gravitational pool intensifies and they
grow faster eventually they generate so
much heat and pressure that they ignite
Fusion reactions and a new Star is Born
but this puts a limit on their size
nuclear fusion releases enough radiation
energy that the surrounding gas cloud is
blown away the new baby star can't
gather more Mass from now on the star is
living on the edge between two forces
gravity pulling in trying to squash the
star and radiation created by Fusion
pushing outwards trying to blow the star
apart after millions or billions of
years is the core runs out of fuel and
the balance brakes destroying the star
but black hole stars were very very
different the beasts of the early
Universe a few hundred million years
after the big bang when the universe was
much smaller all the matter in existence
was much more
concentrated the universe was much
denser and hotter Dark Matter was a
dominant player forming giant structures
called Dark Matter halos these dark
matter Halos were so massive that they
pulled in and concentrated unimaginably
gigantic amounts of hydrogen gas
becoming the birthplaces of the first
stars and galaxies epic clouds of
hydrogen formed some as massive as 100
Million Suns more than the mass of small
galaxies in this unique environment that
will never exist again the enormous
gravitational pull of the Dark Matter
Halos Drew gas into its Center and
created extremely massive stars
as we said before when A Star is Born it
blows away the gas cloud that created it
but these Titanic gas cloud in the early
Universe was so large and massive that
even after their birth more and more gas
piled on the newborn star making it grow
to unbelievable proportions the young
star is forced to grow and grow and grow
getting more and more massive until in
some cases it reaches up to 10 million
times the mass of our sun crushed by
gravity
its core gets hotter and hotter
desperately pushing outwards trying to
blow itself apart but to no avail
there's too much mass and too much
pressure the balance is impossible to
uphold like a supernova run fast forward
the core gets crushed into a black hole
normally that would be the end today
stars go supernova a black hole forms
and things calm down but in this case
the star survives its own death a
tremendous explosion rocks the star from
the inside but it's not enough the star
is so large and massive that not even a
supernova can destroy it but now it has
a black hole for a heart it's tiny a few
tens of kilometers in the center of a
thing the size of the solar
system the monster
grows Stars Are Born from ever faster
spinning and collapsing gas and so they
also spin when a black hole is born from
the core of a star it keeps its angular
momentum this means that matter that
gets drawn in doesn't just fall in a
straight line but instead begins
orbiting the black hole in smaller and
smaller circles going faster and faster
the result is an accretion disc where
gas orbits at nearly the speed of light
only a small amount of gas actually
falls in at any given moment basically
black holes put a lot of food on the
table and only nibble at it but the
matter trapped in the accretion disc
doesn't have a good time friction and
collisions between particles heated up
to temperatures of millions of deg
actively feeding black holes have
accretion discs that are incredibly hot
and Powerful this heat from the disc
further restricts how much a black hole
can devour just like the core of stars
the super hot material creates radiation
that blows away most of the food within
its reach so even if a black hole had
access to as much food as it desired it
can only grow slowly a black hole
embedded inside ins a black hole star is
different the enormous pressure
surrounding it pushes down matter
directly into the black hole overcoming
all restrictions on how fast it can
consume this process is so violent and
releases so much energy that the
accretion disc becomes hotter and
releases more radiation pressure than
any star core ever could enough to push
back against the weight of 10 million
Suns an impossibly dangerous balance has
been created millions of soda masses
pushing in the angry radiation of a
force-fed black hole pushing out for the
next few million years the black hole
star is consumed from within the black
hole grows to thousands of solar masses
and the bigger it gets the faster it
eats which heats up the star even more
and causes it to expand in its Final
Phase the black hole star has become
over 30 times wider than our solar
system truly the largest star to ever
exist in the the universe the intense
magnetic fields at its core spew out
Jets of plasma from the black hole's
poles which Pierce through the star and
shoot out into space turning it into a
cosmic Beacon it must have been one of
the most a inducing SES to ever exist in
the
universe but this also marks the end it
becomes too stretched and the accretion
disc within too powerful the parasite
destroys its host blowing it apart a
black hole hole with the mass of 100,000
Suns rips its way out to hunt for new
prey while leaving behind nothing but a
star
carcass the super massive question if
black hole Stars existed they could
explain one of the greatest Mysteries of
the universe the super massive black
holes we see at the center of galaxies
are just too big they shouldn't be
possible black holes born from regular
supernovas can be a few tens of solar
masses at most and because of the
process we explained before they grow
slowly after that if black holes merge
they can form slightly larger black
holes of over a 100 solar masses it
should take billions and billions of
years to make black holes with hundreds
of thousands or even millions of solar
masses and yet we know that some super
massive black holes already had 800
million solar masses only 690 million
years after the big bang black hole
stars are a sort of black hole cheek
coat if they formed very early in our
universe and the black holes that
emerged from them were thousands of
solar masses then they could be the
seeds for super massive black holes
these seeds could take root in the
center of the earliest galaxies merging
with others and drawing in enough matter
to grow quickly and
reliably very soon we may be able to
verify their past existence the James
web Space Telescope is turning its sens
is to explore the farthest reaches of
the universe looking back in time back
to the early universe that we couldn't
see before so with luck we might be able
to witness glimpses of these tragic
Titans in the brief moment between their
formation and
destruction until then let's do the
visual Journey again just for fun stars
are big black hole Stars bigger
[Music]
[Applause]