welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy today we will learn about
blizzards what is a
blizzard a blizzard is a natural
occurrence it describes a very powerful
and severe
snowstorm for a snowstorm to be
considered a blizzard it must have very
powerful winds low temperatures and a
lot of blow in
snow how are blizzards
formed for a blizzard to form there has
to be key
elements the air in the clouds must be
below the freezing point to allow for
the formation of
snowflakes the air on the ground must
also be below the freezing
point moisture in the air known as water
vapor is also important
when Wind Blows across large bodies of
water it picks up a lot of water vapor
which contributes to the formation of a
blizzard finally there has to be a time
when warm air meets cold air this
combination of air of differing
temperatures helps to create the
occurrence of a
blizzard when and where do blizzards
form blizzards are winter storms and
they can happen anywhere that it
snows however they seem to happen more
prevalently in the northeastern region
of the United States and in the
providences of
Canada blizzard
features there are key features to keep
in mind when determining if a snowstorm
is in fact a
blizzard first there has to be sustained
wind speeds of 35 mph or 56 km hour or
greater for at least 3
hours as mentioned before blowing snow
is also a characteristic of a blizzard
the snow blowing around reduces our
ability to see very
far blizzards reduce our visibility to
approximately 1/4 of a mile or4 kilm or
less when visibility becomes so low
driving conditions will become
increasingly more
dangerous blizzards also occur with very
low
temperatures temperatures can drop below
10° F or -12°
C consequences of a
blizzard when blizzard conditions occur
roads and transportation systems May may
be
affected white out conditions occur when
a severe blizzard becomes so dangerous
that it is difficult to see where the
ground ends and the air
begins this presents a greater challenge
for anyone trying to move around
outside people often lose their sense of
direction when operating a motor vehicle
or aircraft and accidents may happen
blizzard conditions can have devastating
effects lack of access to food or
medical care can leave long-term damages
for anyone trapped by the copious
amounts of snow associated with
blizzards extreme temperatures can lead
to hypothermia and loss of
life extreme temperatures can also
affect machine
and electronics necessary for the daily
operation of our
communities what can be done to prevent
a
blizzard as with other natural
occurrences a blizzard cannot be
prevented people living in blizzard
prone regions can however prepare for a
blizzard should one
occur meteorologists and other weather
specialists
will issue a blizzard watch if they have
predicted weather conditions that may
lead to a
blizzard in this case people are
encouraged to stay indoors with
emergency supplies like food water and
medical
supplies blizzards can have serious
consequences the strong winds extremely
cold temperatures and the snow blowing
around can lead to the accumulation of
snow which which can lead to loss of
lives being aware of their causes and
effects on the environment is one way to
be prepared in the event of a blizzard
happening in your
area I hope you learned something about
blizzards today thank you for taking
this Learning Journey with me until next
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
EA Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our
Channel