welcome to eza homeschool academy
life cycle of a chicken
which came first
the chicken or the egg
this is an age-old question and the
answer varies based on whom you ask
today we will explore the life cycle of
a chicken
but first we will learn a bit more about
them
chickens belong to the vertebrae of
birds
they have small heads
pointy beets and feathers on their
bodies
chickens are omnivores which means they
eat both plants and animals
they eat seeds
grass
grains
lizards
toads and even mice
[Music]
there are more than 500 breeds of
chicken across the world
there are more than 25 billion
individual chickens worldwide
there are more chickens in the world
than any other bird
adult male chickens are called roosters
male chickens under one year are called
cockrills
[Music]
adult female chickens are called hens
female chickens under one year are
called pulitz
newly hatched birds are called chicks
chickens are highly intelligent
can remember faces
and can learn new behaviors
chickens play a major role in our
society
they are raised worldwide for their meat
and their eggs
[Music]
now that we've learned a little bit more
about chickens let's learn about their
life cycle
the life of a chicken begins in a
fertilized egg
while in the egg the chicken grows and
changes
it takes approximately 21 days for the
transformation in the egg to be
completed
[Music]
this is stage one of the chicken's life
cycle
the egg
let us take a look at what happens
inside the egg as the chick develops
over the 21-day period
[Music]
after approximately 21 days the chick
will begin cracking the eggshell from
the inside using its egg tooth in an
effort to get out
[Music]
stage two of a chicken's life cycle
occurs once the hatchling emerges from
the egg
the chick will take time to regain its
strength and dry out its feathers
these chickens shown here are in the
third stage of the life cycle
they will grow and change
molting is one way they will
change they push out old feathers and
grow new ones
adulthood marks stage four of a
chicken's life cycle
as stated previously adult males are
called roosters while adult females are
called hens
[Music]
let's review
as stated before the life of a chicken
starts in a fertilized egg
the egg goes through a major
transformation and it takes
approximately 21 days
the chicken side will grow and change
after 21 days
the chick will hatch from its egg
that chick will grow
and mold and get new feathers
all the way up until adulthood
that is the life cycle of a gym
chickens are super smart ahen and her
chicks communicate while they are still
in their eggs
overall so much can be said about these
beautiful creatures
as with all animals they play an
important part in our natural ecosystem
let us work together to make sure they
are around for a long time
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email easy a homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel