welcome to eza homeschool academy
hi
today we're talking about dragonflies
dragonflies are some of the oldest
insects on earth
scientists believe they have lived on
earth for millions of years
dragonflies are invertebrates more
specifically arthropods since they are
insects they have six legs a thorax and
an abdomen
most people know them for their long
bodies transparent wings and big eyes
[Music]
dragonflies live all over the world in
warm climates and near water
they are carnivores and will eat
mosquitoes cicadas flies gnats and even
other dragonflies
a dragonfly has two compound eyes and
inside those eyes it has over 30 000
smaller eyes
this allows the dragonfly to have an
almost 360 degree view of its
surroundings their eyesight is almost
like a superpower
[Music]
dragonflies have magnificent wings they
have two sets of wings attached to their
thorax which allows them to fly in any
direction
unlike most creatures they can fly
sideways and backwards too
this ability makes them fantastic
hunters they are stealthy and will often
capture and eat their prey
all while flying
dragonflies belong to the odaneta group
of insects
odon is the greek word for tooth
while dragonflies don't have true teeth
they do have very strong mandibles which
aids in capturing prey
[Music]
dragonflies can be found in a variety of
sizes and colors
they are some of the most colorful
creatures in the insect world
let's take a look at the dragonfly's
life cycle
dragonflies like most insects go through
metamorphosis and look very different at
each stage of life
dragonflies start life in an egg that is
laid on plants near water or directly in
water
larvae will hatch from the egg and stay
in water for up to one to five years
when it is ready it will crawl out of
the water and nymphs will emerge after
molting as they continue to grow
adult dragonflies can live from a few
weeks to about one year before dying
dragonflies are ectothermic and spend
time in the sun to raise their body
temperature
this time in the sun warms them up and
readies them for flying
dragonflies are awesome creatures and
eat a lot they are great for the
ecosystem because they eat creatures
like mosquitoes and gnats which humans
consider pests
dragonflies are a source of inspiration
for engineers and people have been
studying this incredible creature in an
effort to make robots that have
dragonfly qualities
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easy a
homeschool academy at yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel