welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
today we will learn about droughts
what is a drought
a drought is a natural occurrence that
takes place when there is a continuous
period of drier than normal weather
conditions that lead to a shortage of
water
lack of precipitation in the form of
rain or snow can affect the moisture
content in the atmosphere in the soil as
well as the water levels in underground
water sources Rivers streams and lakes
what causes a drought
one of the following occurrences usually
causes droughts
lack of precipitation
lack of rain and or low levels of
rainfall can lead to a drought
droughts usually occur in areas that
already receive very little rainfall
if that amount lowers even just a little
it can be devastating for that region
atmospheric changes
in some regions of the world there are
distinct wet and dry seasons
these weather changes affect the levels
of water in that area
during the dry season when dry air is
being moved across the region watering
holes May dry up and edible plants will
dry out sooner
animals in this region usually migrate
to other locations until rains return
erosion
natural processes like wind water and
gravity can affect the movement of soil
if these factors move already dry soil
around it can affect the plant life in
the affected region
this can worsen the effects of a drought
what are the main types of droughts
it is difficult to pinpoint exactly when
a drought begins and ends because it
takes place over an extended period
this occurrence can affect both plants
and animals alike
droughts can last weeks months or even
years
here are the main types of droughts
meteorological
meteorological droughts are weather
related and happens when there is a
continuous time that an area receives
less than average precipitation
agricultural droughts are related to the
production of food and affects crop
output or the natural environment of a
distinct area
this usually occurs when there is not
enough water in the region to sustain
the plant life
therefore less problems are produced
hydrological
hydrological droughts are related to the
fresh water resources available on Earth
this type of drought happens when the
levels of groundwater lakes and other
bodies of fresh water drops below their
normal amount
when water sources are depleted and are
not replaced it can lead to a
hydrological drought
consequences of droughts
droughts occur when the land in a region
is too dry
this lack of moisture can have
catastrophic effects on the people
animals and plants in a given region
here are some of the consequences
associated with a drought
Environmental
the lack of precipitation will cause
water levels to drop
living things in that area will have
less access to water
plants often die and this creates
scarcity of food for the animals and
people who need them to survive
additionally animals that live in fresh
water habitats will have to adapt to the
drier environment
economic during periods of drought
farming is greatly affected
the decrease in access to fresh water
will lower the food production of crops
and livestock which creates a domino
effect for food availability
less food is produced so less food is
available for distribution and what is
available will be more expensive as a
result
social
the lack of food and access to water can
lead to malnutrition for people and
animals in some communities
as Wildlife flew further away from their
usual watering holes in search for water
they might venture closer to areas where
humans live
this increases the risk of injury to
humans by wild animals what can be done
to prevent a drought people in drought
prone areas do a few things to protect
themselves against the drought
though since a drought is a natural
occurrence human actions cannot always
prevent it from happening
dance
people build dams and will use them to
provide water to the affected areas in
the event of a drought
rainwater harvesting
some individuals will collect rainwater
and reserve it for use during a drought
mindful land usage
another way in which people living in
drought prone regions Safeguard
themselves is by being mindful of their
land usage in an effort to reduce
erosion
rotating crops and allowing the land to
take breaks between crops is one way to
mitigate against a drought droughts can
have serious consequences the decrease
in water supply can greatly affect
living things in the affected areas
droughts can have long-term effects and
can happen anywhere
being aware of their causes and effects
on the environment is one way to be
prepared in the event of a drought
happening in your area
I hope you learned something about
droughts today
thank you for taking this Learning
Journey until next time
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easya
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com like and
share our videos please subscribe to our
Channel
[Music]