welcome to eza homeschool academy
all about earthquakes
we live on this beautiful planet called
earth
our planet is home to more than 7
billion people
all across the surface of the earth
living things can be found roaming the
lands or dwelling in the waterways
our seemingly still planet
hides a different world
under its surface
the earth is made of four basic layers
a solid crust
a hot
nearly solid mantle
a liquid outer core
and a solid inner core
the crust is the part of the earth we
live and walk on this is a solid layer
that holds the land and the oceans
the mantle right below is almost solid
the top layer of the mantle and the
crust together form the lithosphere
just below the mantle is the outer core
this is an ever moving layer of nickel
and iron
the inner core of the earth is solid and
made up of mostly iron
an earthquake is a powerful shaking of
earth's surface
the cross
the shaking is caused by movements and
pressure in earth's outer core
[Music]
the non-stop movement in the outer core
causes stress on the earth's crust
when the stressors get too much it leads
to cracks in the crust called
faults
[Music]
earthquakes have been recorded on every
continent on earth
though the crust of the earth is solid
it is not one continuous piece
instead it is a group of pieces that fit
together like a huge puzzle
these puzzle pieces are called tectonic
plates
the locations where the tectonic plates
match up are called
fault lines
when tectonic plates move it causes
movement at the faults
an earthquake is the sudden movement of
earth's crust at the fault line
[Music]
scientists and researchers use what is
called a seismograph to measure
earthquakes
there are four causes of earthquakes
the first is tectonic which occur
because of movement of the tectonic
plates
earthquakes are also caused by volcanic
activity
they can come before
or after a volcanic eruption
human activity can also lead to
earthquakes
one such activity is the use of
explosions
nuclear explosions can trigger
earthquakes
another human activity that can trigger
an earthquake is mining
collapse earthquakes occur around mining
caves
[Music]
the area below the surface where the
earthquake starts is called the
hypocenter
[Music]
the area on the surface right above the
hypo center where the earthquake started
is called the epicenter
scientists use these information to
track
record and to find out more about
earthquakes
[Music]
the tectonic plates move in three main
ways during an earthquake
in some cases called a transform or
strike and slip method the tectonic
plates slide past each other
in other cases
we find divergent or
normal movement
in this case the tectonic plates pull
away from each other and new crust is
formed along the fault line
tectonic plates also converge
in this form they will move
towards each other
forming high mountain peaks
this is also called thrust
earthquakes are natural phenomena that
scientists and researchers cannot
predict
earthquakes can be dangerous and can
cause a lot of damage to buildings
roadways and can even flame lives
it is important to know a few ways to
protect oneself in the case of an
earthquake emergency
if you are inside stay inside
drop down to the floor and move under a
sturdy table or desk
cover your head and neck
then hold on to the legs of the table or
disc until the shaking stops
even after the shaking stops it is
important to be careful
walking around
be sure to
watch your footing
as
aftershocks are also known to follow
earthquakes
these are tremors that come after the
main earthquake
one of the most destructive earthquakes
to occur
in u.s history happened in april in 1906
in san francisco california
the quake did not last long however it
triggered other events like fires and
sunburns for three days
there was a lot of devastation after
that earthquake
our vast planet is riddled with mystery
and wonder
there's so much left to be uncovered
so much left to be explored
one thing is for sure
we need to do our part to ensure that
this planet is here for generations to
come
take care of the planet
take care of yourselves
thank you for taking this learning
journey with me
until next time
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email eza homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel
you