welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy electricity and the light bulb
before the discovery of electricity and
the invention of the light bulb life was
ruled by the natural cycle of day and
night as the sun set Darkness enveloped
homes streets and
workplaces people relied on candles oil
lamps and open Flames to light their way
all of which were dim
costly and dangerous nighttime
activities were limited and once the sun
dipped below the Horizon productivity
often came to a halt the world was
waiting for a transformative invention
something that could banish the darkness
and bring light into every corner of
life that change came in the 19th
century thanks to a series of
groundbreaking discoveries and the
contributions of inventors like Thomas
Edison and Nicola Tesla Thomas Edison
was one of the most famous figures
associated with electricity and the
light bulb while he did not invent the
light bulb outright his work was crucial
in making it practical for everyday use
early versions of the light bulb had
been developed in the decades before
Edison but they were inefficient
expensive and shortlived in
1879 Edison patented a more reli
reliable and longer lasting incandescent
bulb he achieved this by using a carbon
filament and creating a vacuum inside
the bulb to prevent the filament from
burning out quickly Edison's bulb could
burn for up to 40 hours a remarkable
Improvement at the time this practical
design made electric lighting accessible
to homes streets and businesses
transforming how people lived and worked
however Edison's light bulb was part of
the larger Revolution for electric
lighting to reach its full potential a
system to deliver electricity
efficiently and safely was needed Nicola
Tesla a brilliant inventor and engineer
played a crucial role in solving this
problem while Edison championed direct
current DC electricity Tesla velop the
alternating current AC system which
could transmit power over long distances
with less energy loss AC power became
the standard for electrical grids
worldwide making it possible to light
entire cities and power homes factories
and
infrastructure Tesla's Innovations also
laid the groundwork for modern
electrical systems including the
Transformers and Motors we rely on today
the invention of the light bulb and the
development of electricity did far more
than simply illuminate the night these
advancements fueled a technological and
Cultural Revolution making life safer
more productive and more connected
factories could Now operate Around the
Clock enabling mass production and
driving economic growth students could
study after sunset workers had more
flexible hours and families could enjoy
evenings together in well-lit rooms
electric lighting also made streets
safer reducing accidents and crime
Beyond lighting electricity became the
foundation for countless Innovations
from the Telegraph and the radio to
televisions computers and
smartphones the world was entering an
era of unprecedented progress all
powered by the invisible force of
electricity the social impact of
electric lighting was profound before
its invention only the wealthiest could
afford the luxury of candles and oil LS
electric light however was affordable
and accessible to the masses it provided
comfort and convenience bringing New
Opportunities For Education work and
Leisure to people of all backgrounds in
cities the glow of electric street
lights transformed night life allowing
shops theaters and restaurants to stay
open late electricity also
revolutionized rural areas bringing
modern conveniences to farms and small
towns that had long relied on
traditional methods the light bulb
became a symbol of innovation and
possibility inspiring new ideas and
inventions Edison's success with the
light bulb spurred the creation of
entire Industries dedicated to
electrical appliances communication
Technologies and power
generation over time electricity would
fuel advances in science medicine and
transportation making it one of the most
essential and versatile discoveries in
human history it's fascinating to note
that Edison and Tesla though often seen
as Rivals both contributed to the
world's electrification in complimentary
ways while Ed light bulb illuminated
homes and factories Tesla's AC system
ensured that electricity could reach
those places
efficiently together their work laid the
foundation for the modern electrical
grid that powers the world today despite
their disagreements their combined
Legacy reminds us of the transformative
power of innovation and
collaboration the invention of the light
bulb and the discovery of electricity
didn't just change the way we live they
changed the way we think about time and
possibilities no longer bound by the
limits of daylight Humanity could extend
its activities into the night explore
New Horizons and create a brighter
future today every time we flip a switch
and light fills our room we are reminded
of the Ingenuity and the perseverance of
the inventors who brought electricity to
the world from the first dim glow of
Edison's bulb to the dazzling cities of
today the Journey of electricity
continues to illuminate our path forward
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email EA
Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel
[Music]