welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
today we will learn about floods
what is a flood
a flood is a natural occurrence in which
land that is usually dry becomes over
saturated with water
this simply means that dry land gets
covered with water
what causes a flood
ing is commonly caused by one of the
following conditions
heavy rainfall
when it rains for long periods of time
and the land is unable to drain the
water before new rain falls it could
lead to flooding
water usually travels from Higher Ground
to lower ground therefore buildings
people and animals or vegetation in
low-lying areas are more prone to
flooding after heavy rainfall
overflowing Rivers
when there is more water in the rivers
than usual this can lead to flooding
if there is heavy rainfall occurring
Upstream putting more water into the
river than the areas Downstream could
become too full and they will overflow
their Banks
a break in a dam
if for any reason there is too much
water behind the dam the force of the
water can cause a break in the dam
this breakage will overflow the Waterway
which can lead to flooding
other natural occurrences
other natural occurrences like
hurricanes Cyclones and tsunamis can
also lead to flooding
these natural occurrences usually bring
strong winds and heavy rains
this can lead to flooding along the
coastline of affected areas
melting snow and ice
Rising temperatures causes ice and snow
to melt
this is part of the natural cycle of
water on Earth
if the temperature rises too quickly and
puts too much water into the waterways
again this can lead to flooding in the
low-lying areas
what are the main types of floods
a flood can occur over several days or
very quickly over several hours
how the flood forms determine its name
a flood that develops over several hours
is called a flash flood
they can happen anywhere but are most
prevalent in low drainage areas
these floods are very dangerous because
they occur with little to no warning and
therefore there can be little to no
preparation
a flood that develops over one to two
days is called a rapid onset flood
these types of floods cause tremendous
damage and individuals living in these
zones usually have very little time to
prepare and evacuate or leave the area
a flood that develops over several days
or weeks is called a slow onset flood
these floods can be just as harmful as
any however because they are slow moving
there is more time to prepare
individuals living in these regions have
more time to gather themselves and their
belongings and move to Higher Ground
a flood that occurs as a result of a
hurricane Cyclone or storm is called a
storm surge flood
when these storm systems come on land
they can bring heavy winds
the winds can bring water onto the land
quickly which can lead to flooding they
are very dangerous and can affect people
living miles away from the coastline
safety guidelines
too much water in an area too quickly
can lead to a flood
individuals living in flood-prone areas
have to be aware of the weather patterns
and conditions that may lead to flooding
if there is a possibility of flooding
there are some things one can do to stay
safe
keep an emergency kit
it is important to keep emergency
supplies and documents in an easily
accessible location so that they can be
retrieved in the event of an emergency
unplug and turn off all appliances in
the home and or business
move to Higher Ground and bring
emergency supplies
stay away from power lines and cables
Above All Else follow the safety
guidelines outlined by local officials
at all times
flood damage can be devastating and can
have long-term effects
local officials are always prepared and
ready to help those affected by floods
stay informed and be prepared if you
live in flood-prone areas
floods are natural occurrences that can
happen anywhere
though they are more prevalent in
low-lying regions it is important for
everyone to know how to respond in the
event of a flood
I hope you learned something about
flooding today thank you for taking this
Learning Journey with me until next time
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easy a
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com like and
share our videos please subscribe to our
Channel
foreign