welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy let's learn about the parts of a
flower a flower also known as a bloom or
Blossom is the reproductive structure
found in flowering
plants its primary function is to
facilitate reproduction or to make seeds
so new plants can grow in this video we
will explore the parts of a flower
this is a
petal petals are often colorful and
conspicuous petals attract pollinators
such as insects birds and
bats here is the
nect the nect of a flower is a special
part that makes nectar a sweet liquid
the nectar is usually found at the base
of the petals nectar attracts animals
like bees butterflies and hummingbirds
which come to the flower to drink the
sweet
liquid when these animals visit the flow
for nectar they often carry pollen from
one flower to another helping the plant
to reproduce and make seeds this is the
seepo the seepo is one of the outer
parts of the flower that looks like
small green leaves seaes are usually
found at the base of of the flower and
form a protective layer around the
flower bud before it
opens they help protect the developing
flower and can also support the petals
when the flower is In
Bloom seaes are often green but in some
flowers they can be colorful like the
petals here is the receptacle which is
the part of the flower where all the
flower parts are attached it acts as the
base that supports the entire flower it
is located at the top of the
stem here is the stem the stem of a
flower is the part that supports the
flower and connects it to the rest of
the
plant it holds up the flower so it can
reach sunlight and be more easily seen
by pollinators like bees and
butterflies the stem also carries water
and nutrients from the roots to the flow
and other parts of the plant now let's
take a look at the pistol this is the
female reproductive part of a flower and
typically has three main parts stigma
the top part of the pistol that is
sticky or feathery designed to catch and
hold pollen style the tube like
structure that connects the stigma to
the ovary it allows pollen to travel
down to reach the ovary ovary the
enlarged base of the pistol that
contains the ovules or the eggs after
fertilization the ovary develops into a
fruit and the ovules become seeds the
pistol is the central structure in a
flower that is involved in seed
production and it involves the stigma
style and
ovary the staman is the male
reproductive organ of a flower
responsible for producing and releasing
pollen it consists of two main parts
anther the top part of the staman where
pollen is produced and stored in sacks
called pollen saxs is also known as the
anther filament the Slender stock-like
part that supports the anther and
positions it for Optimum pollen
dispersal is known as the filament
together the stammen in a flower work to
produce pollen which is then transferred
to the stigma of the pistol for
fertilization ultimately leading to seed
production let's take another look at
the cross-section of a flower showing
all the parts
labeled flowers play a crucial role in
the reproduction of plants by attracting
pollinators like bees butterflies and
and birds which help transfer pollen
between flowers for
fertilization additionally flowers
produce seeds ensuring the continuation
of plant species and
biodiversity I hope you learned
something about the parts of a flower
today thanks for taking this Learning
Journey with me until next time as
always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email EA
Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel
[Music]