welcome to eza homeschool academy
frogs
frogs are amphibians which means they
can live in water or on land the word
amphibian means double life
so these aquatic creatures spend time in
and out of water
there are over 4 000 species of frogs
they are identified by their bulgy eyes
and their smooth wet skin
their hind legs are usually twice as
long as their front legs and most can
jump very
well
here's a quick fun fact tree frogs have
sticky feet because they secrete mucus
the mucus allows them to stick more
easily to the tree as they move around
being amphibious means they need to live
near water
frogs can be found all over the world in
a variety of habitats on every continent
except antarctica
most frogs are brown or green in color
these colorations help them blend in or
camouflage with their surroundings
camouflage is an important survival
technique
these frogs are usually found near ponds
or wetlands in woodlands or in grassy
areas
conversely there are some frogs with
interestingly bright skin colorations
these frogs are usually poisonous and
can be found in the wet tropical forests
of central and south america
ah who's hiding under there
the brightly colored skin pigmentation
is to warn predators of the poison in
their skin
some frogs are so poisonous that one
drop of the skin secretion can kill 10
adult humans
frogs have fantastic eyes
the bulge of the eyes of most frogs
allow them to see in front
to the sides and partially behind them
time for another fun fact
frogs use their eyeballs to push their
food down when swallowing
let's talk briefly about the life cycle
of a frog
frogs start life in soft eggs
from the eggs tadpoles hatch
over time the tadpoles grow larger
as they do
their tails shrink and they grow legs
froglets form when both sets of legs
grow on the tadpole
the tail of the froglet continues to
shrink and nourish the body
the metamorphosis is complete when the
tail is completely absorbed by the body
time for another fun fact
a group of frogs is called an army
frog calls are unique to their species
with each having their own special sound
some croaks are so loud they can be
heard from one mile away
you guessed it time for another fun fact
frogs absorb water through their skin
instead of drinking
frogs have excellent night vision which
is another great survival technique as
they are usually nocturnal
nocturnal means they are most active at
night
did you know all toads are frogs but not
all frogs are toads
huh
makes you wonder
frogs are mysteriously beautiful and
appear in a variety of sizes look at all
these beautiful frogs
are you ready for another fun fact
the goliath frog is the largest in the
world and can be found in the rain
forests of africa
the mini mum frog is the smallest in the
world and can also be found in africa
frogs are a mysteriously beautiful
species
they are helpful to humans as they eat
animals that are considered pests
they eat other animals like insects
moths snails slugs and worms
larger frogs will eat fish
crabs birds and even small mammals
frogs a wonderful group of interesting
animals
thankfully conservation efforts are in
place to help maintain and preserve
their habitats they are an awesome group
of animals
hey
why are frogs rarely angry
because they eat everything that bugs
them
thanks for taking the time to learn
about frogs with me today until next
time
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email easy a homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel