welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy let's learn about the systems of
the human body the human body is a
complex and highly organized structure
made up of cells tissues and organs each
playing a vital role in maintaining the
body's overall function and health to
understand how the body works it is
essential to learn about the different
systems that make up this intricate
organism
each system consists of specific organs
and structures that work together to
perform particular tasks the immune
system is like the body's defense Army
it's made up of various cells tissues
and organs that work together to protect
the body from harmful Invaders like
bacteria viruses and other
pathogens without it the body would be
vulnerable to infections and diseases
the immune system also helps the body
heal from injuries and fight off
illnesses here are some key components
of the immune system white blood cells
also known as lucaites
these are the soldiers of the immune
system they circulate through the body
in the bloodstream and are always on the
lookout for Invaders when they detect a
threat they spring into action ready to
fight they there are different types of
white blood cells each with a specific
role in defending the body lymph
nodes lymph nodes are small bean-shaped
structures that act like checkpoints
they filter harmful substances and
contain immune cells that help fight
infection when you're sick your lymph
nodes might swell as they work hard to
combat the infection
spleen the the spleen is like a large
filter for your blood it helps remove
old or damaged blood cells and also
plays a role in detecting and responding
to infections thymus the thymus is a
small organ where some white blood cells
known as te- cells mature and learn to
distinguish between the body's own cells
and harmful Invaders bone marrow this is
the soft tissue inside bones where new
blood cells including white blood cells
are produced it's like a factory for the
immune system
antibodies these are special proteins
produced by the white blood cells that
help identify and neutralize specific
Invaders each antibody is designed to
Target a specific pathogen like a lock
and key system skin and and mucus
membranes these are the first lines of
Defense acting as physical barriers to
keep harmful substances out the skin
covers the entire body while mucous
membranes line the respiratory Digestive
and other tracts the immune system is
like a complex and well-coordinated army
that protects the body from countless
threats just like a house needs a
security system to keep safe your body
relies on the immune system to stay
healthy and strong Additionally the
immune system has a memory which means
it can remember past Invaders and
respond more quickly if they attack
again in the future to help boost your
immune system it is important to
maintain a healthy balanced diet I hope
you learned something about the immune
system of the human body today thanks
for taking this Learning Journey with me
until next time as always thank you for
watching tell us what you want to see
next email eah Homeschool Academy
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel
[Music]