welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
hurricane
today we will be learning about
hurricanes
what is a hurricane
a hurricane is a big powerful storm that
starts over warm ocean water in the
tropics it has very strong winds and
lots of rain
[Music]
hurricanes have different names
depending on the region of the world
where they occur
for example in the Atlantic Ocean and
Northeast Pacific Ocean hurricanes are
also called tropical Cyclones or simply
Cyclones
in the Northwest Pacific Ocean
hurricanes are known as typhoons
in the South Pacific and Indian Ocean
hurricanes are called severe tropical
Cyclones
regardless of the name used these storms
all have the same basic characteristics
of strong winds heavy rain and potential
for significant damage
foreign
how are hurricanes formed
hurricanes are formed through a
combination of warm ocean water moisture
in the atmosphere and certain weather
conditions
[Music]
first the sun heats up the surface of
the ocean causing it to evaporate and
release water vapor into the air
the water vapor Rises and cools as it
goes higher into the atmosphere
when it cools it forms clouds
as more water vapor is released into the
air the clouds become bigger and bigger
this is called a tropical disturbance
if certain conditions are met such as
warm ocean water and low wind shear the
tropical disturbance can continue to
grow and intensify into a tropical
depression
[Music]
if the tropical depression continues to
strengthen it becomes a tropical storm
with wind speeds up 39 to 73 miles per
hour
finally if the storm's winds reach 74
miles per hour or greater it is
classified as a hurricane
once a hurricane has formed it can
travel across the ocean and potentially
make landfall causing significant damage
and posing a danger to people and
property in its path
have you ever wondered how fast a
hurricane moves
the speed of a hurricane can vary widely
depending on a variety of factors
including the location and size of the
storm as well as the wind and weather
conditions in the surrounding area
however on average a hurricane moves at
a speed of around 10 to 20 miles per
hour or 16 to 32 kilometers per hour
when it is over Open Water
once a hurricane makes landfall its
speed can slow down significantly and it
may even stall over a particular area
resulting in heavy rainfall and flooding
it's important to note that while the
speed of a hurricane can be measured its
impact and potential for damage are
determined by a combination of factors
including wind speed storm surge and the
amount of rainfall it produces
what are the parts of a hurricane
a hurricane is a complex storm system
with several distinct Parts here are
just some of the parts of a hurricane
the eye
the eye of the storm is the calm center
of the hurricane typically around 20 to
40 miles or 32 to 64 kilometers in
diameter
eye wall
the area surrounding the eye were the
most intense winds heaviest rain and
strongest weather conditions occur is
called the eye wall
rain bands
bands of clouds and precipitation that
spiral outward from the center of the
hurricane are called rain bands
these can extend hundreds of miles from
the eye and produce significant rainfall
and flooding
outflow
the upper level winds that flow out of
the top of the hurricane are called the
outflow these help to ventilate and
strengthen the storm
[Music]
storm surge a rise in sea level that can
occur when A hurricane's winds push
water toward the shore are called Storm
surges this can result in significant
flooding in coastal areas
[Music]
tornadoes
some hurricanes can produce tornadoes
which can cause additional damage and
pose a significant threat to life and
property
[Music]
understanding the different parts of a
hurricane can help people prepare for
and respond to these dangerous storms
it's important to follow weather
forecasts and emergency instructions
from authorities to stay safe during a
hurricane
here are some tips to help you stay safe
during a hurricane
stay informed listen to weather reports
and emergency alerts on the radio
television or other sources keep up to
date on the latest developments and
instructions from local authorities
[Music]
prepare for emergencies with an
emergency kit
pack a bag with essential supplies like
food water clothing first aid supplies
and medications make sure to have enough
supplies to last for several days
secure your home
make sure to secure windows and doors
and to bring outdoor furniture and other
items indoors if you live in a flood
prone area consider elevating furniture
and appliances off the floor
[Music]
evacuate if necessary if local
authorities advise evacuation follow
their instructions and evacuate
immediately listen to emergency
personnel and move to Higher Ground if
necessary
stay safe during the storm
if you can't evacuate stay inside and
away from Windows and Doors if the power
goes out use flashlights or battery
operated lanterns instead of candles
avoid using electrical appliances and
stay away from flood waters which may be
contaminated or have dangerous currents
by following these tips persons can stay
safe during a hurricane and reduce the
risk of injury or property damage
remember to always listen to local
authorities and emergency personnel and
take necessary precautions to stay safe
I hope you learned something about
hurricanes today these big powerful
storms that start over warm water can be
dangerous always be on alert
thank you for taking this Learning
Journey with me until next time
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easya
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com like and
share our videos please subscribe to our
Channel
thank you