at its height the Roman Empire was home
to about 30% of the world's population
and in many ways it was the Pinnacle of
human advancement its citizens enjoyed
the benefits of central heating concrete
double glazing banking international
trade and upward social Mobility Rome
became the first city in history with 1
million inhabitants and was a center of
technological legal and economic
progress an Empire impos possible to
topple stable and Rich and Powerful
until it wasn't anymore first slowly
then suddenly the most powerful
civilization on Earth collapsed by
civilization we mean a complex society
where labor is specialized and social
classes emerge and which is ruled by
institutions civilizations share a
dominant Mutual language and culture and
domesticate plants and animals to feed
and sustain large cities where they
offer and construct impressive
monuments civilization lets us become
efficient on large scales collect vast
amounts of knowledge and put human
Ingenuity and the natural resources of
the world to work without civilization
most people would never have been born
which makes it a bit concerning that
collapse is the rule not the exception
virtually all civilizations end on
average after 340 years collapse is
rarely nice for for individuals their
shared cultural identity is shattered as
institutions lose the power to organize
people knowledge is lost living
standards fall violence increases and
often the population declines the
civilization either completely
disappears is absorbed by stronger
neighbors or something new emerges
sometimes with more primitive technology
than
before if this is how it's been over the
ages what about us today
[Music]
just as Europeans forgot how to build
indoor plumbing and make cement will we
lose our industrial technology and with
that our greatest achievements from $1
Pizza to smartphones or laser eye
surgery will all this go away too today
our cities stretch 4 thousands of square
km we travel the skies our communication
is instant in industrial agriculture
with engineered high yield plants
efficient machinery and high potency
fertilizer feeds billions of people
modern medicine gives us the longest
lifespan we've ever had while industrial
technology gives us an unprecedented
level of comfort and abundance even
though we haven't yet learned to attain
them without destroying our
ecosphere there are arguably still
different civilizations around today
that compete and coexist with each other
but together they also form a singular
Global
civilization but this modern globalized
civilization is even more vulnerable in
some ways than past Empires because we
are much more deeply
interconnected a collapse of the
industrialized World literally means
that the majority of people alive today
would perish since without industrial
agriculture we would no longer be able
to feed them and there's an even greater
risk what if a collapse was so deeply d
structive that we were unable to
reindustrialize again what if it ruined
our chances of enjoying a flourishing
future as a multiplanetary
species a global civilizational collapse
could be an existential catastrophe
something that ruins not just the lives
of everyone alive today but all the
future Generations that could have come
into being all the knowledge we might
have discovered the art we might have
created the joys we might have
experienced would be lost so How likely
is all of this let's start with some
good news while civilization collapses
have happened regularly none have ever
derailed the course of global
civilization Rome collapsed but the
axite Empire or the tequin and of course
the bantine Empire carried on what about
sudden population
crashes so far we've not seen a
catastrophe that has killed much more
than 10% of the global population no
pandemic no natural disaster no war the
last clear example of a rapid global
population decrease was the Black Death
a pandemic of the Bubonic plague in the
14th century that spread across the
Middle East and Europe and killed a
third of all Europeans and about one/
tenth of the global population if any
event was going to cause the collapse of
civilization that should have been it
but even the Black Death demonstrates
Humanity's resilience more than its
fragility while the old societies were
massively disrup Ed in the short term
the intense loss of human lives and
suffering did little too negatively
impact European economic and
technological development in the long
run population size recovered within two
centuries and just two centuries later
the Industrial Revolution began history
is full of incredible recoveries from
horrible
tragedies take the atomic bombing of
Hiroshima during World War
II 140,000 people were killed and 90% of
the city was at least partially
incinerated or reduced to Rubble but
Against All Odds they made a remarkable
recovery hiroshima's population
recovered within a decade and today it's
a thriving city of 1.2 million people
none of this made these horrible events
any less horrible for those who live
through them but for us as a species
these signs of resilience are good
news why recovery is likely even in the
worst
case one thing that's different from
historic la is is that Humanity now has
unprecedented destructive power today's
nuclear arsenals are so powerful that
all out global war could cause a nuclear
winter and billions of deaths our
knowledge of our own biology and how to
manipulate it is getting so Advanced
that it's becoming possible to engineer
viruses as contagious as the Corona
virus and as deadly as
Ebola increasingly the risk of global
pandemics is much higher than in the
past so we may cause a collapse
ourselves and it might be much worse
than the things Nature has thrown at us
so far but if say 99% of the population
died would Global civilization collapse
forever could we recover from such a
tragedy we have some reasons to be
optimistic let's start with food there
are 1 billion agricultural workers today
so even if the global population fa to
just 80 million it's virtually
guaranteed that many survivors would
know how to produce food and and we
don't need to start at square one
because we could still use modern high
yield crops mazee is 10 times bigger
than its wild ancestor ancient Tomatoes
were the size of today's pece after
agriculture the next step towards
recovery would be rebuilding industrial
capacity like power grids and automated
manufacturing a huge problem is that our
economies of scale make it impossible to
just pick up where we left off many of
our high-tech Industries are only
functional because of huge demand and
intensely interconnected Supply chains
across different continents even if our
infrastructure were left unharmed we
would make huge steps backwards
technologically but then again we are
thinking in larger time frames
industrialization originally happened
12,000 years after the Agricultural
Revolution so if we need to start over
after a massive collapse it shouldn't be
that hard to reindustrialize at least on
evolutionary time scales
there's a hitch though the Industrial
Revolution was fueled literally by
burning easily accessible coal and we
are still very much reliant on it if we
use it all up today aside from making
rapid climate change much worse we could
hinder our ability to recover from a
huge crisis so we should stop using easy
to access coal so it can serve as a
civilization Insurance in case something
bad happens another thing that makes
recovery likely is that we'd probably
have most of the we need to rebuild
civilization we would certainly lose a
lot of crucial institutional knowledge
especially on hard drives that nobody
could read or operate anymore but a lot
of the technological scientific and
cultural knowledge stored in the world's
2.6 million libraries would survive the
catastrophe the post collapse survivors
would know what used to be possible and
they could reverse engineer some of the
tools and machines they'd find in
conclusion despite the Bleak Prospect of
catastrophic threats natural or Crea by
ourselves there is reason for optimism
humankind is remarkably resilient and
even in the case of a global
civilizational collapse it seems likely
that we would be able to recover even if
many people were to perish or suffer
immense hardship even if we lost
cultural and technological achievements
in the process but given the stakes the
risks are still unnervingly high nuclear
war and dangerous pandemics threaten the
amazing global civiliz Iz ation we have
built humanity is like a teenager
speeding around blind Corners drunk
without a seat belt the good news is
that it's still early enough to prepare
for and to mitigate these risks we just
need to actually do it
[Music]