[Music]
when our vegetarian ancestors started
eating meat around 2 million years ago
it wasn't just because animals taste
great it was pure necessity climate
change made many of the plants our
ancestors relied on less available and
meat bridged that Gap from the discovery
of fire at the latest meat became a
staple of the human diet but over the
last few years eating meat has
increasingly been associated with health
risks like heart disease certain Cancers
and an early death so how unhealthy is
meat
[Music]
really in this video we'll only talk
about meat dairy products deserve a
video of their own biologically we need
to eat for three reasons for energy to
acquire materials to fabricate our cells
and to get special mole that our bodies
can't make themselves the energy and
most of the materials come from the
three macronutrients fats carbohydrates
and
proteins proteins are the most important
resource for repairing and replenishing
our cells structures the special
molecules are a large variety of
vitamins and minerals we need to drive
metabolic
processes meat provides us with most of
these things it contains all essential
amino acids our body needs and a lot of
minerals like iron zinc and essential
vitamins some of which are barely found
in plants like vitamin B12 only one
essential nutrient is missing in most of
the meat we consume vitamin C it appears
in almost all plants and supports our
immune system as well as the development
of connective tissues after a few months
without it you'd get
scurvy but meat has another big
Advantage its high
bioavailability so some of the nutrients
in meat are broken down faster and
available quicker than those from Plants
spinach for example contains more iron
than meat but it's absorbed much slower
and the body needs more energy to digest
it several health benefits have also
been observed in communities that rely
solely on meat the Inu for example are
able to survive in extreme climate
conditions on a purely meat-based diet
if necessary since they consume the
whole animal including the organs they
get every single nutrient they need
including vitamin C so meat itself is
definitely not dangerous for us but its
health effects vary depending on how
it's prepared and what animal it comes
from when talking about meat in the
Western World We generally mean muscle
tissues that have a high nutrient
density but also lack some of the
vitamins that make it possible to
survive on meat alone the most healthy
animals to eat are probably fish fish
contain contains polyunsaturated fatty
acids like omega-3 which may lower the
risk of cardiovascular diseases and
support anti-inflammatory immune
functions as part of a balanced diet
Fish can be eaten regularly without
worries eating fish comes with its own
bag of complications though like over
fishing and the destruction of the
oceans we'll talk about that in another
video a close second is the most popular
meat chicken it's regarded as the meat
with the EST health risks the only
negative Health effect of poultry is a
bit controversial fat its high content
of saturated fats is associated with a
higher cholesterol level and
cardiovascular
disease but this idea has also been
criticized by a large number of
scientists arguing high cholesterol
levels might be inherited and not caused
by
nutrition so in general if you want meat
and are concerned about your health go
for chicken
things start to get problematic with
high intakes of red meats like beef ve
pork lamb horse and goat a recently
published study recommends for example a
maximum of 23 g of red meat per day
which is a very small stake per week
however large scale metaanalysis Studies
have shown that eating 100 G of red meat
every day increases the relative risk of
Diabetes by 19% of Strokes by 11% and of
chorl cancer by
177% this sounds alarming but before we
Panic let's have a look at how these
studies were
conducted because this brings us to the
second big problem when trying to answer
the question of whether meat is
unhealthy or not most studies that
linked health risks to eating red meat
were case control studies which means
taking a group of people with a disease
and classifying them by their eating
habits the more red meat they consume
the more likely they were to contract
certain diseases the problem is that
it's very hard to eliminate other
factors people who eat less meat tend to
live a healthier lifestyle in general
they tend to eat more vegetables and
fruit and are less likely to smoke and
drink
alcohol most studies try to eliminate
these factors but it's extremely hard to
make definitive
statements things get worse when we look
at processed meat though processing meat
means adding certain chemicals by curing
smoking salting or fermenting or in
other words making it delicious bacon
ham salami sausages and hot dogs contain
chemicals that are harmful for us like
nitrates and nitrites that can damage
the DNA in our digestive system and lead
to cancer the wh reviewed 800 studies
over 20 years and concluded that
processed meat is strongly linked to an
increased risk of Choral cancer each
extra 50 g of processed meat meat per
day increases your relative risk of
cancer by 18% when it comes to cancer
risk processed meat is now in the same
category as plutonium Asbestos and
smoking The Who highlights that its
research is only about the question of
whether or not something causes cancer
and not to what extent but processed
meat may also significantly increase the
chance of suffering from diabetes
strokes and coronary heart
diseases it also makes to difference
what sort of life our meat lived when it
was still part of a living being it's
common to feed large amounts of
antibiotics to Livestock in order to
prevent diseases which can spread
antibiotic
resistance combined a high consumption
of both red and processed meat could
increase your chance of premature death
by up to
29% this means if your chance of dying
is 3% this year it's now
4% this might not sound like a lot but
tiny percentages have a huge impact on
societies of
millions they also seem harmless until
they affect you to blame meat alone for
bad Health would be wrong though there
is no evidence that the very essence of
meat has any negative effect Beyond its
high fat content and even this point is
highly
contentious just like with many other
Pleasures in life sometimes too much of
a good thing is harmful most public
health agencies suggest cutting meat
consumption to f 500 g a week while
studies suggest cutting down processed
meat as much as
possible so if you Feast on meat no more
than once or twice a week you should be
good for most people this already means
a drastic change in their diets though
the average American consumes around
almost 1,600 G of meat a week the
average German 1,100 g a week and many
of us eat much much more if you're not
really sure make us small note whenever
you eat meat for a week or two you'll be
surprised how much it really is so most
people watching this video would benefit
from cutting down on
meat aside from health concerns there's
still the fact that the meat industry is
one of the largest contributors to
climate change and has reached a scale
where it's impossible to deliver
millions of tons of meat and still treat
animals with dignity we've already
discussed that in detail in another
video all in all in moderation meat is
not unhealthy and you don't need to
become vegetarian overnight to have a
real impact on your health and the
planet but your lifestyle choices do
matter for yourself and for others