over the last few years organic food has
spread like wildfire despite higher
prices buying organic is turning from an
alternative into a moral and social
responsibility organic food is
supposedly healthier more natural and
more ethical but what do we even mean
when we say
organic there's no Global consensus so
different regions have different
definitions and rules in general organic
food food is farmed without GMO seeds
synthetic fertilizers or synthetic
pesticides instead organic farmers use
more traditional ways of producing food
like crop rotation and use organic
fertilizers such as compost or manure
while the motivation to buy organic food
is clearly Noble is it actually
effective or just another costly Trend
we can skip without feeling guilty
[Music]
is organic food healthier one idea
associated with Organic crops is that
their natural cultivation is supposed to
make them more nutritious and healthier
indeed several studies found that
organic foods contain more
antioxidants plants produce them as a
sort of homemade pesticide organic
plants seem to have to work a little
harder while regular plants have plenty
of help from humans antioxidants are
believed to have some health benefits
although scientists are still on the
fence about them in general we have no
idea if and how exactly they help us or
how much produce you'd have to eat to
absorb a certain
amount what about organic being more
nutritious well the evidence is mixed
some studies found that organic food can
have slightly higher concentrations of
vitamin C and omega-3 fatty acids While
others did not find significant
differences
overall the mixed evidence suggests that
there are only small differences in
nutritional value so from the science
available so far it doesn't look like
organic food has significant health
benefits what we do know is that eating
fruit and veggies in general is good for
you and most of us don't do that enough
eating veggies is more important for
your health than how they were
produced is organic food more natural
people don't only buy organic to get
extra vitamins but to avoid something
toxic artificial pesticides and
fertilizers and indeed several studies
show that there actually is less
pesticide residue on organic produce but
here's where things get
complicated less pesticide does not mean
none at all while pesticides are
supposed to be a last resort in organic
farming they're not forbidden most
Organic pesticides are natural toxins
like vegetable oils potach soap sulfur
or copper sulfates but there are
synthetic substances as well what's the
difference between organic and regular
pesticides not a lot actually Organic
pesticides are not necessarily safer
than conventional ones toxic is toxic no
matter if the substance is manufactured
or derived from nature in fact in the
case of copper sulfate often used on
organic apples the organic pesticide of
choice is actually more harmful to
humans the toxicity of any substance
depends on its concentration and your
exposure to it not if it's natural or
not there are few recent studies about
how our current level of pesticide
exposure affects our long-term Health a
2018 study from France Associated never
eating organic food with a higher risk
of certain
cancers the study was criticized a lot
though the participants reported their
dietary habits themselves while no
actual tests of pesticide levels in
their bodies were done complicating
things even more a Danish study from
2018 found that the danger from
pesticides for an adult was similar to
drinking a glass of wine every 3 months
the pesticides on your vegetables are
nothing to lose
sleepover despite this we should
continue to demand strict standards for
our food all pesticides are regulated
and tested very strictly in the EU and
the US
every year thousands of food samples are
screened for
pesticides the majority of samples have
no residues or just a fraction of the
tolerance level right now contamination
from bacteria and fungi is much more
dangerous and on this front the risk is
the same be it organic or regular
food is organic food better for the
environment in 2017 a meta analysis
looked at organic farming in detail
and analyzed organic and regular foods
from over 700 production sources and
their impact on categories like
greenhouse gas emissions energy
consumption and land needs the result no
production method is clearly better for
the
environment organic systems use less
energy than conventional ones but have
similar greenhouse gas emissions Organic
Farms use less pesticide but need much
more land to produce the same amount of
crop these mixed results were also
confirmed by a report from the Swedish
food agency organic and regular were
equal in most regards the biggest
difference was land use and here
conventional farming clearly won and
ecotoxicity where organic farming has a
clear
Advantage so according to these results
conventional farming actually has a
little bit less impact on the
environment compared to organic the
bottom line is organic food isn't
Superior to regular produce as far as we
know but organic agriculture also has an
impact at a broader level demand is
rising constantly and the struggle to
supply the market can lead to production
methods that are less sustainable in
other ways Spain for example grows tons
of regular and organic vegetables
destined for export in vast Greenhouse
areas which use a lot of energy and have
other environmental impacts such as
significantly higher greenhouse gas
emissions and because growing demand
can't be covered by domestic production
the global trade in organic foods is
also increasing as Supply chains get
more and more complex to make all kinds
of foods available in organic quality
ensuring organic quality standards and
regulations gets ever more difficult
this has led to incidences of fraud
where conventional food was labeled and
sold as expensive organic produce but
organic versus conventional food isn't
even an objective discussion
organic is not simply a production
method for many it's an ideology buying
organic feels right people want to do
the correct thing for the health of
their children and the well-being of the
planet but our instinct to think of
organic as good and conventional as bad
can get in the way of making the most
reasonable
decision the solution could be to stop
seeing organic and conventional farming
as irreconcilable they both have pros
and cons and the best way to produce
healthy food efficiently would be a
combination of their best
features and as for your personal
shopping what food you should buy
depends on what you expect from it if
you simply want to eat healthily you
should buy more fruit and veggies of any
kind not necessarily organic if your
concern is for the environment then
simply buying organic won't solve this
problem for you the easiest option is to
buy local food that's in season
basically seasonal is the true organic
to sum up an organic label is a
manufacturing notice not a security
certificate or a silver bullet for your
diet what you eat is much more important
than how it's produced