do you think the European Union is worth
it or should we end it many people feel
a strong disconnect with the EU While
others praise its
achievements everything considered is
its existence good or bad for
[Music]
Europeans since it looks like the UK is
leaving the EU will mostly treat it as
if it's no longer part of the club the
European Union combining its 27 member
countries has a population of about 450
million people making it the third most
populous sort of country in the world
it's the world's second largest economy
by GDP and has the biggest single Market
in the world but originally the creation
of the European Union was all about one
thing
peace Europeans are really good at War
so they were embroiled in bloody
conflicts for basically all their
history a century long rivalry between
Germany and France alone cost millions
of lives and ran so deeply the Germans
invented their own word for it e fine
shaft after the second world war
Europeans decided they wanted lasting
peace that was not based on a balance of
military power instead the economies
politics and peoples of Europe should
become so closely interconnected that
war would become both imprac iCal and
Unthinkable the plan worked between EU
members we've had over 70 years of
Peace okay peace is great and all but
what are the European Union's
achievements and
problems today EU citizens benefit from
many individual freedoms EU treaties and
regulations ensure easy travel cheap
telecommunications a great variety of
goods and services as well as very
strong health and safety standards
European institutions are not afraid to
pick a fight with companies such as
Microsoft Apple or Facebook about Fair
competition tax evasion or data
protection through the EU science
programs the European countries became a
collaborative engine that serves as a
hub of Science in The Wider World
unrestricted travel and the right to
work anywhere makes it easy to apply for
funds and set up International Teams of
experts with the best equipment in turn
the EU became the world leader in terms
of its Global share of science research
and produces more than 25% of the
world's research output with only 5% of
its
population but many citizens feel
distrust towards the EU Brussels seems
far away and untransparent
technocratic and difficult to understand
it doesn't help that the EU is terrible
at Outreach and explaining what it
actually
does this disconnect has also led to an
Ever shrinking voter turnout over the
decades more transparency and
accountability are desperately needed if
the EU institutions want the trust of
their citizens currently the EU is still
shaken by the refugee crisis of
2015 some countries have accepted far
greater numbers of Asylum Seekers than
others while the Border countries are
overwhelmed and feel left alone other
countries are shocked by the initially
unregulated Mass immigration and closed
their borders effectively shutting down
the largest route into Europe the eu's
wealth and freedom make it an attractive
destination and this is unlikely to
change the population is split on how to
react to that some argue that Europe let
in too many immigrants with a different
culture without strictly demanding
integration While others argue that
immigration is not the problem but that
racism and discrimination of immigrants
is preventing
integration to strike a balance between
helping refugees turning illegal
immigrants away and successfully integ
in the ones that stay remains one of the
most difficult and controversial
challenges of the Union immigration
aside many more challenges lie in the
future like defense traditionally
European countries have relied strongly
on the protection of the us through
NATO but in the current political
climate Europe has to ask itself if it
really wants to depend on the United
States for its safety if combined today
the militaries of EU members could form
an effective defensive force and be the
third largest military in the world that
could save a lot of money Safeguard
European borders and enhance cultural
understanding with soldiers from 27
different countries serving one common
purpose what about money well it's
complicated the EU created the largest
single Market in the world inside it you
can trade border and Customs free
countries that entered it got a massive
boost to their economies even between
neighbors trade increased by up to 500%
and there was a steady creation of new
jobs research has suggested that joining
the EU has left most new members with an
average of a 12% higher GDP than if they
had remained outside and for those
regions with weaker economies and poor
infrastructure EU institutions provide
billions of Euros every year helping
economic investment infrastructure and
Social
Development on the negative side the EU
tries to hold together countries with v
ly different economies and laws
regarding labor taxes and Social
Security the cost of 1 hour of work in
an EU country ranges from €4 an hour to
€40 an hour some countries have large
Industries and strong exports While
others focus on Services tourism or
natural resources on top of this the
euro is the common currency of some but
not all of these
countries as the Greek crisis shows this
can be a recipe for
disaster you cannot unify vastly
different economies under one currency
but leave their economic policies
separate so should all EU countries
unite under the common currency or not
should the weakest links be thrown out
of the Euro or should countries be made
to adopt common policies on taxes
healthare and Social Security it's a
question that's been brewing for years
and is nowhere near a
solution so everything briefly
considered is the European Union worth
it here is our answer the EU is very
flawed and still needs a lot of work but
it's fair to say that the European Union
makes Europeans powerful in the world
put together we lead in science are one
of the strongest economic powers and
could have one of the strongest
militaries in the world but more
importantly the EU gives us peace
security and a sense of shared identity
and something we all Crave in these
turbulent times
stability if we want to protect the
values we're so proud of a strong
European Union is the best way to make
sure our voice is heard in the world
alone as small states we'll hardly stand
a chance in a world of Shifting
superpowers what do you think about the
EU and its future in recent years the
discussion about political topics has
become super toxic with sad real world
consequences let's not do that if you
don't agree with this video you're not
our enemy you just have a different
opinion and that's fine we're all in the
same boat after all so let's have a
fact-based discussion about our future
[Music]