welcome to easy a homeschool academy
let's learn about the life cycle of a
ladybug
ladybugs are some of the most loved
beetles around
they are distinguishable by their little
red
orange or yellow bodies and most people
would identify them by their spots
ladybugs are insects and have the
distinctive features
they have a head
a thorax
six legs
an abdomen
and wings
their wings are actually hidden until
they are ready to fly the colored hard
shell that they are known for protects
the body when they are not in flight
ladybugs are sometimes called lady
beetles or ladybird beetles
they are invertebrates because they do
not have a backbone
there are over 5 000 species of ladybugs
worldwide
here is a map showing the distribution
of ladybugs worldwide
as you can see they can be found
everywhere except in the arctic
and antarctic regions where it is too
old
ladybugs can be found in a variety of
habitats
forests
grasslands
near bodies of water
in city parks or gardens
in suburbs and even on farms
these beautiful creatures can have
anywhere from 0 to 24 spots
the number of spots a ladybug has
helps to identify the species
spots along with its bright red orange
or yellow coloration
is a warning to predators to stay away
it lets the predators know that they
taste
bad some ladybugs have white spots and
other species even have stripes
in addition to their coloration
ladybugs protect themselves
by releasing a foul smelling liquid from
their bodies
predators do not like the smell and will
leave them alone
ladybugs will also play dead if they
feel threatened
ladybugs are omnivores which means they
eat both plants and animals
depending on the species they will eat
plant parts like stems and leaves
nectar
pollen or other insects
the most common food are aphids which
are slow-moving
wingless bugs
farmers particularly love ladybugs
because they eat the aphids which
usually destroy the crops
now that we know a little more about
these wonderful creatures
let's discuss their life cycle
ladybugs go through a complete
metamorphosis
as they move through their stages of
life
the life of a ladybug starts in an egg
female ladybugs often lay three to five
eggs in clusters on a leaf or near prey
so food would be readily available when
they hatch
[Music]
in 3 to 10 days the ladybug larva will
emerge from their eggs
they are usually very hungry and can eat
350 to 400 aphids in a span of two
weeks
the larva that emerge from the eggs do
not look like the adults
they have elongated bodies
a bumpy exoskeleton and brightly colored
bands or spots on their backs
they will grow and molt up to four times
before they are ready for the next stage
of life
in this stage of life the ladybug pupae
attaches itself to a leaf
and remains very still
for seven to ten days
during this time the pupae undergoes a
big change
all the cells in its body are moved
around to form the adult ladybug
nature is fascinating
after the pupa stage adult or mature
ladybugs emerge
newly emerged ladybugs are pale
and have soft exoskeletons which makes
them a prime target for predators
after some time their exoskeletons will
harden
and they will gain their signature
bright colorations and spots
let's review
a ladybug goes through a complete
metamorphosis
from egg
to the larval stage
to the pupil stage
and finally
to the adult stage of life
ladybugs are most active in the spring
and fall
when temperatures are warmer
once the temperature gets cold they look
for ideal places for hibernation
they hibernate under rocks
in rotting logs
or in buildings
ladybugs will also cluster together for
warmth
or to intensify their scent to further
protect them
from predators
like all creatures ladybugs have a place
in their natural ecosystem
in many cultures they are a sign of good
fortune
positivity
and success
they are fascinating little creatures
thanks for coming along with us today as
we learned about the life cycle of
ladybug
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email eza homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel