welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy today we are going to learn
about the layers of the Earth's
atmosphere Earth is surrounded by a
system of air called the
atmosphere the atmosphere is made up of
a combination of gases mainly nitrogen
and
oxygen there are also Trace Amounts of
other gases like carb carbon dioxide and
water
vapor all of these gases play an
important role in sustaining life here
on
Earth nitrogen plays a major role in the
life cycle of plants they need this gas
to transform the nutrients into energy
which most plants need to
grow oxygen is also a necessary gas that
all living things depend
on pla plants use carbon dioxide during
a process called
photosynthesis and it helps with the
regulation of Earth's
temperature water vapor is in the air
and is part of the water
cycle these gases along with temperature
and air pressure make up Earth's
[Music]
atmosphere the levels of air pressure
and temperature of the air changes as
the layers of the atmosphere
change the further away from the earth
go the less air pressure one will
feel the air pressure is the amount of
force caused by the surrounding
air air pressure is the greatest on the
surface of the
Earth the gravitational pull of the
Earth's surface on the air keeps the
atmosphere in
place the temperature can change
depending on the layer of the
atmosphere there are five main layers of
the
atmosphere the first and closest layer
to the Earth is the
troposphere this is where we live and it
extends to about 7 m or 12 km
high in this layer you will find all the
air that living things need to
survive it is where clouds and most of
our weather forms
the air is dense enough in this layer to
support the flight of birds and
airplanes the next layer of the
atmosphere starts where the troposphere
stops and stretches about 30 Mi or 49 km
high this layer is called the
Stratosphere in this layer you will find
the ozone layer and this is the layer
that absorbs most of the radiation from
the Sun
the mesosphere is the next layer that
stretches upward about 53 Mi or 83 km it
is very cold here this is where meteor
showers or shooting stars
appear this happens as Space Rock enters
Earth's atmosphere the friction and heat
created by the Rocks hitting the gases
in this layer causes them to burn up and
glow
the thermosphere is the layer above the
mesosphere and it stretches about 435 or
more miles or 700 or more
kilomet here is where the northern and
southern lights
occur this phenomenon is possible
because of the reaction between solar
particles and the gases in this
[Music]
layer the outermost layer of Earth's
atmosphere sphere is called the
exosphere this stretches from 500 or
more miles or 700 or more kilm high this
is the layer where you find satellites
orbiting the
[Music]
earth now we know that gases air
pressure and temperature are all
important aspects of Earth's
atmosphere we also know that there are
five layers of the
atmosphere they are the
troposphere
Stratosphere
mesosphere
thermosphere and
exosphere Earth's atmosphere is
essential for sustaining
life I hope you learned something about
the layers of Earth's atmosphere today
thanks for taking this Learning Journey
with me until next time as always thank
you for watching in tell us what you
want to see next email EA Homeschool
Academy
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel