let's shrink Earth to half its size it
now has a diameter of roughly 6,400 km
and only 1/8 of its former mass is left
just like a rotating ice skater that
pulls in their arms the decreased size
leads to faster rotation one full day
now lasts only 45 minutes also gravity
changes on a half-sized earth all
objects would be half as heavy with
lower gravity walking or running
consumes less energy and we can cover
longer distances on foot however we'd
also be a bit slower furthermore large
parts of our atmosphere would Fade Away
into space since gravity isn't strong
enough to hold it less atmosphere means
less oxygen and CO2 so you should bring
an oxygen Mass to your next outdoor
activity if you don't want to risk
suffocating also with the weaker pull of
gravity the bones and muscles of humans
and animals would become thinner and
weaker and the size and shape of trees
would change significantly due to lower
gravity in the thinner atmosphere
overall we live in a very different
world