welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy let's learn about the life cycle
of a
bean a bean is a living thing that
requires sunlight water and air to grow
there are seven stages in the life cycle
of a
bean stage one the seed
stage the life cycle of a bean plant
begins as a seed when we plant the seed
in soil if the seed gets all the things
it needs to grow
water sunlight and air then a
transformation will
happen even though we can't see it under
the soil the seed will start to swell
and grow roots which anchor the plant
and absorb water and nutrients from the
soil
[Music]
stage two the germination
stage this is when the magic happens the
seed starts to sprout and grow into a
little plant you might see a tiny Chute
popping out of the soil that's the baby
bean plant breaking
through the Chute grows towards the
sunlight while the roots keep growing
downwards into the soil
stage three the seedling stage in this
stage the little shoot has leaves the
plant is still small but it's growing
fast it needs plenty of water and
sunlight to keep growing
strong sometimes we might see the seed
coat still attached to the leaves but it
will eventually fall off
stage four the vegetative stage in this
stage the plant is getting bigger and
stronger it is making more leaves and
branches during this stage the bean
plant focuses on growing lots of green
leaves these leaves help the plant to
make food through a process called
photosynthesis
[Music]
stage five the flowering stage this is
when things start to get even more
exciting the bean plant grows
flowers these flowers are where the
magic of making beans
happens inside the flowers there are
tiny Parts called pollen and
ovaries pollen from one flower needs to
reach the ovary of another another
flower for beans to
form the pollen moves around thanks to
pollinators like
bees
ladybugs
butterflies and
[Music]
hummingbirds stage six the fruiting
stage after successful pollination the
flowers start start to fade away and the
little pods start to
form inside these pods are the baby
beans as the pods grow bigger the beans
inside grow
too when the pots are ready they'll turn
brown and that's when we know it's time
to harvest the
[Music]
beans stage seven the maturation
stage the beans inside the pods continue
to grow and develop until they're fully
mature at this point the plant stops
growing and it starts focusing on making
sure the seeds are ready for the next
generation of bean
[Music]
plants so let's
review there are seven stages in the
life cycle of a bean
plant the seed
stage the germination
stage the seedling
stage the vegetative
stage the flowering
stage the fruiting
stage and the maturation
stage each stage is an important part of
the process and life cycle of a
being it's pretty amazing how a tiny
seed can grow into a big beautiful plant
that gives us yummy beans to
[Music]
eat I hope you learned something about
the life cycle of beans today thanks for
taking this Learning Journey with me
until next
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
ezaa Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel