hi there are some things that are
quintessential to the fall season
and one of them
is the abundance of apples
today let's think about the life cycle
of an apple
the life of an apple starts as a seed
those seeds are planted in soil where
they will begin to grow
after some time the seeds will emerge
from the soil as sprouts
after three to five years buds will form
on the tree
the buds will then create blossoms
these beautiful blossoms attract
pollinators like bees to the apple tree
after about 10 days the blossoms will
fall off the tree and apples will begin
to form in their place
soon the apple tree will be full of ripe
fruit ready for picking
then you can head over to the orchard
and fill your basket with delicious
apples
[Music]
the apples that are left over at the end
of the season will rot and provide
nutrients for the soil
there you have it the life cycle of an
apple
starts out as seeds which are planted in
soil and will sprout a tree
that tree will form buds
which will form blossoms
eventually the blossoms
will fall off the tree
[Music]
as always thank you for watching
please like our videos and subscribe to
our channel
[Music]