welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
life in the coral reefs
[Music]
come with me today as we take a closer
look at Coral Reef life
what is a coral reef
a coral reef is an underwater community
that is created by tiny animals called
Coral polyps
[Music]
these polyps create an exoskeleton out
of calcium carbonate which keeps them
safe and protected
coral reefs are home to many colorful
fish plants and other sea creatures it's
like a busy neighborhood in the ocean
what are some animals you might see in a
coral reef thank you
[Music]
octopus
although they are Masters of Disguise
some species of octopuses can be found
living near coral reefs you using coral
structures for shelter they also use
their arms to search the crevices of the
reef for food
stingrays
graceful and flat stingrays can often be
spotted Gliding Over Sandy patches near
the coral reef searching for food
they can be found in a variety of colors
and with interesting patterns
Blue Tang
this vibrant blue fish with a
distinctive Yellow Tail can be found
swimming near coral reefs feeding on
algae
more eels
these slender snake-like creatures can
be seen hiding in crevices and holes
within the coral reef waiting to Ambush
their prey
sea stars
sea stars also known as starfish are
common Reef dwellers these beautiful
creatures with their in radical symmetry
can be found crawling along the Sandy
areas or Coral structures of the reef
[Music]
clownfish these colorful fish live among
the tentacles of sea anemones forming a
symbiotic relationship
a symbiotic relationship is a special
kind of relationship between different
living things
it is when two or more organisms work
together and help each other in some way
parrotfish these vibrant fish have
beak-like mouths and help keep the reef
healthy by eating algae and dead coral
did you know that parrot fish are known
to play a role in the creation of sand
inside the parrotfish's digestive system
the coral and rock fragments are ground
up and broken down
over time the accumulation of these fine
particles contributes to the formation
of sandy beaches and Islands
[Music]
seahorses
these small fascinating fish are masters
of camouflage blending in with the
corals as they cling to them using their
curly tails
seahorses appear in a variety of colors
and with interesting patterns
sea turtles
various species of sea turtles such as
the green sea turtle and the hawk spill
Turtle can be found swimming in and
around coral reefs
reef shark
the reef shark also known as the black
tip reef shark is a common shark species
found in many tropical coral reefs they
are relatively small and typically not
considered dangerous to humans
coral reefs are home to a vast array of
colorful fish sea turtles sharks and
other fascinating creatures each animal
has its own role to play in The Reef
ecosystem
coral reefs provide shelter and
protection for many marine organisms
they also support a variety of plants
and algae which provide food and oxygen
for the reef inhabitants
coral reefs are facing many challenges
pollution
overfishing and coral bleaching are some
of the threats that can harm the
delicate balance of the reef ecosystem
it's important to take care of coral
reefs and help protect them we can do
this by learning about them reducing our
use of plastics that can harm marine
life and taking steps to preserve the
health of our oceans
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easy a
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com like and
share our videos please subscribe to our
Channel
[Music]