welcome to eza homeschool academy
apple fun
this is an apple
[Music]
an apple is a fruit that grows on a tree
all living things have a life cycle
the life of an apple starts as a seed
[Music]
those seeds are planted in soil where
they will begin to grow
after some time the seeds will emerge
from the soil as sprout
buds on the tree means it's ready to
make fruit
[Music]
blossoms will form in the place of the
buds
[Music]
pollinators like bees will come to help
the tree make new fruits
[Music]
once the blossoms fall off the tree
apples will grow in their place
[Music]
the life cycle starts over from seed
to sprout
buds to blossoms
and finally to fruit on the tree
[Music]
if more fruit is produced than is needed
the apples that fall to the ground will
decompose or rot
becoming nourishment for the soil
[Music]
apples can be used to make many things
however they are just as delicious all
on their own
[Music]
as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next
email eza homeschool academy at
yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our channel