welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
life in the garden
come with me today as we take a closer
look at backyard gardens
backyard gardens can be considered micro
habitats because of the diversity of
living things that can be found there
they are wonderful places to relax play
and enjoy nature
some Gardens primarily have flowers
While others may have fruit trees and
bushes or even vegetables
Gardens of all types are wonderful
places for animals to visit
animals can be found in these micro
habitats because they provide all or
some of the things they need to survive
here animals can find shelter food space
to grow and change water and plenty of
fresh air
let's look around the garden to see who
has come to visit
look I see a butterfly
butterflies are insects they have a head
a thorax and an abdomen they also have
six legs
birds of all shapes sizes and colors are
popular backyard animals they are
pollinators which means they help plants
make more of themselves by moving pollen
around
look I see a beetle
beetles are great Garden helpers they
use their antennae on their heads to
smell and touch the world around them
ah look a spider
spiders are arachnids they have eight
legs and use their webs to trap their
prey
can you see the squirrel
did you know squirrels often use their
fluffy Tails as a blanket to stay warm
wow it's a salamander if there are damp
areas in a garden salamanders might come
to visit they have wet skin so they need
areas that have a lot of moisture
another common sighting in gardens are
ants
ants live in groups called colonies and
they work together to take care of each
other
frogs can also be found in some Gardens
they are wonderful garden helpers
because they eat the animals some people
might consider to be pests like
mosquitoes
look closely do you see the Hedgehog
hedgehogs are mammals they are covered
in Prickly spines that they use to
protect themselves when they feel
threatened
some insects and slugs can be harmful to
Gardens and these backyard reptiles are
here to help
lizards eat the animals some people may
consider to be pests
take a look at this creature it is a
slug
slugs move around thanks to the mucus
they produce that allows them to slide
over and climb various services
toads are common Garden dwellers too
they usually have dry bumpy skin
they keep Gardens pest free by eating
potentially harmful bugs
oh look a bee bees are attracted to the
bright colors in flowers they live in
groups called colonies they love to
drink the nectar of the flowers they use
the nectar to make honey
rabbits are often shy creatures so you
have to be very stealthy to be able to
observe them
did you know their teeth never stop
growing
Wild
Gardens are a great place to spot local
Wildlife but they can also be a place
where we also get food
some people like to plant food in their
Gardens
carrots are loved by many people and
they can be eaten cooked or raw
strawberries are another favorite and
are usually the first fruits to ripen in
the spring
Swiss Chard is a part of the leafy
greens family it has been used since
ancient times to treat many illnesses
tomatoes are commonly planted in
backyard gardens
there are thousands of varieties and
they can be pink purple black or even
White
kale is a member of the Cabbage family
it is a very healthy option to have in
the garden it can be eaten raw or cooked
these are raspberries
they are healthy and nutritious
they are eaten in a variety of ways and
are often used in desserts
check out these cucumbers
cucumbers are great as part of a meal or
a snack they contain a lot of water
which helps to keep us hydrated
backyard gardens are a great way to grow
the foods we love
what is your favorite garden food
whether you are just relaxing or ready
to explore
Gardens are a great place to find out
more
they may contain yummy foods or animals
Galore
go take a look Now's the Time for a tour
[Music]
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easy a
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com
like and share our videos please
subscribe to our Channel