hi today we're thinking about fall and
here in the northern hemisphere that
means cooler winds and the leaves will
start changing soon
one sure sign of fall
is pumpkins
today let's think about the life cycle
of a pumpkin
believe it or not pumpkins are fruits
and they come in a variety of colors
shapes and sizes
how does a pumpkin grow
the life of a pumpkin starts as a seed
seeds are planted in the soil where they
grow
[Music]
soon vines begin to grow and produce
brussels
blossoms grow and fall off the vines
[Music]
now there's a baby pumpkin
that baby pumpkin will grow and grow and
eventually change from green to orange
look closely do you see it changing
[Music]
soon the pumpkin is ready
now you can head to the
pumpkin patch and find the perfect
pumpkin
[Music]
cut open the pumpkin and you will find
lots of seeds inside
some people like to dry them and eat
them
[Music]
some use the pumpkin to make pies
pumpkins can also be used to make donuts
they can be used to make soup and so
much more
many people use them to make
jack-o-lanterns
[Music]
don't worry about the pumpkins that
never get chosen at the patch
they will rot and
continue to nourish the soil for the
next pumpkin season
there you have it the life cycle of a
pumpkin
starts out as a seed that grows into a
vine which will eventually blossom and
produce a baby pumpkin that will grow
and grow until it becomes the perfect
pumpkin for you
[Music]
thank you for watching if you enjoyed
this video please like it and subscribe
to our channel
[Music]