how does lightning work let's slow down
time inside a thundercloud soft hail
bumps into snowflakes and gets
negatively charged by snatching an
electron from a snowflake turbulent
winds carry the light snowflakes upwards
leaving the heavier hail below now the
bottom of the cloud has many more
electrons than it needs and it really
wants to get rid of them an invisible
Street extends towards the ground a
Channel of conductive air called a
leader that Scouts for an electron
disposal site in small steps branching
occasionally meanwhile small electric
arms Sprout from the positively charged
ground reaching for the leader their
handshake is brutal electrons Rush
towards the contact Point creating a
plasma Highway of 50,000 de CSUS that
runs up the leader into the cloud with
1/3 of the speed of light this is what
we see as a lightning bolt the sudden
heat generates a shock wave that we can
hear as thunder in a matter of
milliseconds up to 5 gigles of energy
are transferred to the ground enough to
power an average American household for
over a month and all of this in just the
blink of an eye