welcome to Easy A Homeschool Academy
our planet is made up of a vast variety
of things
some of those things are called living
things While others are called
non-living things
[Music]
additionally living things are called
organisms
how can we determine if something is
living or non-living
there are special features to look out
for when making this determination
[Music]
all living things need some form of
energy or nutrients like food
some living things take in nutrients by
eating While others like plants will
make their own food by using the energy
from the Sun through a process called
photosynthesis
[Music]
all living things also need water to
survive
this includes both plants and animals
with the supply of nutrients and water
all living things will grow and change
some will grow to a certain size then
stop
[Music]
While others will grow continuously
throughout their lifetime
all living things adapt to changes in
their environment for example when birds
migrate to warmer areas for nesting and
breeding
or when an animal's fur color changes to
match the season so they can better
camouflage
even when a human puts on a winter coat
they are adapting to the changes in
their environments
these are always in which living things
adapt to changes in their environment
all living things reproduce or make more
of themselves
they do this by making seeds
[Music]
or by having babies through live births
or laying eggs
[Music]
when making the distinction one should
ask the following questions
[Music]
does this thing need food or water
does it grow or change
does it reproduce
does it react to changes in the
environment
[Music]
if the answer is yes to all of these
questions then it is a living thing
if the answers are no then it is a
non-living thing
[Music]
let's try to determine if the following
are living or non-living things
[Music]
foreign
living things come in all shapes colors
and sizes
they need food and water
[Music]
they grow and change
they adapt to changes in their
environment
and they reproduce
take a walk around your neighborhood
visit a park or Zoo
how many living things can you find
thanks for taking this Learning Journey
with me until next time keep learning
[Music]
as always thank you for watching tell us
what you want to see next email easy a
homeschoolacademy at yahoo.com like and
share our videos please subscribe to our
Channel