over the last decade milk has become a
bit
controversial some people say it's a
necessary and nutritious food vital for
healthy bones but others say it can
cause cancer and lead to an early death
so who's right and why are we drinking
it
[Music]
anyway milk is the basis of every
mammal's diet after birth when our
Digest systems are immature and
small basically it's power food to
Kickstart our bodies and help us grow
milk is rich in fat vitamins minerals
and milk sugar
lactose on top of that for a while after
birth it also contains antibodies and
proteins that protect us from infections
and regulate our immune system but it's
a lot of effort for mothers to produce
eventually humans stop drinking mother's
milk and transition to the diet of their
parents
this is how it's been for thousands of
years until about 11,000 years ago when
our ancestors settled down in the first
agricultural communities soon they
domesticated the first dairy animals
goats sheep and
cattle they found that dairy animals are
able to eat useless and abundant stuff
and turn it into nutritious and tasty
food this made a huge difference in
terms of survival especially in hard
times so groups that had milk available
had an evolutionary
advantage and through natural selection
it changed the genes of communities who
consumed a lot of
it this adaptation has to do with a
specialized enzyme lactase babies have a
lot of it in their system so they can
break down the milk sugar lactose and
digest milk easily but the older we grow
the fewer lactase enzymes our body
produces worldwide about 65% of the
population do not have the enzyme after
infancy which means they are not able to
digest more than about 150 millit each
day this lactose intolerance is not
spread evenly around the world though in
some East Asian communities for example
it's up to
90% in northern Europe and North America
the rates are the lowest
overall there are probably a few reasons
for this uneven distribution the trait
was first introduced by random mutation
which happened independently of each
other in a few populations
the fact that farming replaced hunting
and Gathering more and more created
natural selection
pressure people who were able to digest
lactose had more Foods at hand which was
an advantage the migration of Dairy
Farmers to the north then spread it
further which probably pushed back
populations there that didn't have the
trait okay but if milk has been a
valuable part of our diet for thousands
of years why is it so controversial
there are a number of claims regarding
the negative and positive health effects
of milk the negative ones cover a wide
variety from brittle bones to cancer and
cardiovascular diseases to intolerance
and allergies so how do they hold up
some older studies found a connection
between milk and a high risk of breast
colon and prostate
cancer but metaanalyses found no impact
on your cancer rate
on the contrary the calcium in milk
might even have a protective effect
against colog cancer although this could
be calcium in general it's not clear
milk plays a role in this effect only
studies on prostate cancer showed an
increased risk for people who consumed
more than 1 and a/4 liters of milk a day
but again the association is
inconsistent and other studies don't
find any effect we discuss these studies
in more detail in our sources document
all in all the research seems to show
that if you drink between 100 to 250 ml
of milk per day cancer is not a
concern similarly meta analyses could
not find any impact from milk or dairy
products on your risk of heart disease
stroke or your total
mortality some studies even suggested
that high blood pressure might be rarer
in people who eat a lot of dairy
although the evidence is not strong
enough to claim this with
confidence the case gets more comp
complicated though when we look at bones
a number of studies found neither
positive nor negative effects for adults
what most people worry most about though
are harmful amounts of pesticides
antibiotics or hormones there are
hormones in milk but only in very low
concentrations for example to get the
same amount of hormones as from the pill
you'd need to drink about 5,000 lers of
milk and even if you did most hormones
would be destroyed by your digestive
system before they could affect you
which is the reason why so much
medication is coated to protect it from
our digestion for pesticides and
antibiotics there are regulations in
most parts of the world that only allow
completely harmless amounts milk that
surpasses these thresholds is not
allowed to go on the Shelf so there's
nothing in particular to worry about
besides allergies and those suffering
from lactose intolerances the best known
negative effects of milk are probably
acne and general discomfort after
drinking milk or eating dairy products
and here the effects are very real for
example skimmed milk has been found to
statistically increase the rate of acne
by 24% allergies against milk products
are especially prevalent among children
with one in 18 kids in Germany suffering
from them in general these allergies
tend to get better or disappear as they
grow older though okay is milk healthy
then milk no matter if it comes from
mothers cows sheep goats or or camels is
a nutrient-dense food it contains all
necessary macronutrients and many
micronutrients especially in regions
where people struggle to get enough
calories milk can contribute to a
healthy life and lower child
mortality for those living in the
developed World in general milk is not
harmful if you are not allergic or
intolerant to it especially for children
it's a good way to get large amounts of
calcium and for vegetarians it's a good
source of vitamin B B12 and B vitamins
in general this does not mean there are
not other Alternatives with the same
effect you do not need to drink milk to
be
healthy milk is also definitely not a
substitute for water milk is power food
and the additional canaries from
drinking a lot of it on a regular basis
can contribute to being
overweight especially flavored milk or
chocolate milk is more comparable to
beverages like lemonade than a healthy
snack and there's another thing to
consider milk production has a
significant impact on the global
climate about 33% of cropland is used to
feed grazing animals including dairy
cattle even though the carbon footprint
of dairy products has declined since
1990 Dairy production is still
responsible for 3% of all greenhouse gas
emissions even more than all airplanes
combined milk is a huge industry and
sadly most of its production in factory
farms causes incredible
suffering cows are impregnated over and
over separated from their young shortly
after birth and slaughtered once their
tortured bodies are not productive
anymore we can't ignore that much of the
milk we consume stems from an industry
that is basically torture and
contributes to climate
change what about plant-based
milk in terms of protein levels and
nutritional value only soy milk can
compare to cow milk the others need to
be artificially enriched to reach
similar levels of vitamins and calcium
so they can be an alternative to
milk and another option might be
available soon several startups have
created non-an Animal milk that is
nutritionally identical to dairy milk
for example through fermentation by Gene
modified
bacteria this lap grown milk can even be
turned into cheese something the
plant-based alternative struggle with
because they lack casine and whey
protein the key ingredients that give
Dairy its taste and
structure the environmental impact is a
different story though many milk
Alternatives use significantly less
energy land and less water to produce so
they have a much lower environmental
impact than animal milk if you want to
have the lowest possible negative impact
on the planet the best choice is
whatever milk alternative is
regional as with almost any topic milk
is complicated it's not harmful for the
majority of the population and it's
crucial for many people around the world
it's good nutritious food but also
harmful to the planet and causes a lot
of suffering we need to decide as a
society how we want to deal with these
facts