neutron stars are one of the most
extreme and violent things in the
universe giant atomic nuclei only a few
kilometers in diameter but as massive as
stars and they owe their existence to
the death of something
[Music]
Majestic Stars exist because of a
fragile balance the mass of millions of
billions of trillions of tons of hot
plasma are being pulled inwards by
gravity and squeeze material together
with so much force that nuclei fuse
hydrogen fuses into helium this releases
energy which pushes Against Gravity and
tries to escape as long as this balance
exists stars are pretty
stable eventually the hydrogen will be
exhausted
medium stars like our sun go through a
giant phase where they burn helium into
carbon and oxygen before they eventually
turn into white dwarfs but in Stars many
times the mass of our sun things get
interesting when the helium is exhausted
for a moment the balance of pressure and
radiation tips and gravity winds
squeezing the star tighter than before
the core Burns hotter and faster while
the outer layers of the star swell by
hundreds of times fusing heavier and
heavier elements carbon Burns to Neon in
centuries neon to oxygen in a year
oxygen to Silicon in months and silicon
to iron in a day and then
death ion is nuclear Ash it has no
energy to give and cannot be fused the
fusion suddenly stops and the balance
ends without the outward pressure from
Fusion the core is crushed by the
enormous weight of the star above it
what happens now is awesome and scary
particles like electrons and protons
really don't want to be near each other
but the pressure of the collapsing star
is so great that electrons and protons
fuse into neutrons which then get
squeezed together as tightly as in
atomic
nuclei an iron ball the size of the
Earth is squeezed into a ball of pure
nuclear matter the size of a city but
not just the core the whole star
implodes gravity pulling the outer
layers in at 25% the speed of light this
implosion bounces off the iron core
producing a shock wave that explodes
outwards and catapults the rest of the
star into space this is what we call a
supernova explosion and it will outshine
entire
galaxies what remains of the star is now
a neutron star its mass is around a
million times the mass of the Earth but
compressed to an object about 25 km wide
it's so dense that the mass of all all
living humans would fit into 1 cubic cm
of neutron star matter that's roughly a
billion tons in a space the size of a
sugar cube put another way that's Mount
Everest in a cup of
coffee from the outside a neutron star
is unbelievably extreme its gravity is
the strongest outside black holes and if
it were any denser it would become one
light is bent around it meaning you can
see the front and parts of the back
their surfaces reach a million de C
compared to a measly 6,000 de for our
sun okay let's look inside a neutron
star although these giant atomic nuclei
are stars in many ways they're also like
planets with solid crusts over a liquid
core the crust is extremely hard the
outermost layers are made of iron left
over from the Supernova squeezed
together in a crystal latice with a sea
of electrons flowing through them going
deeper gravity squeezes nuclei closer
together we find fewer and fewer protons
as most merg to neutrons until we reach
the base of the crust here nuclei are
squeezed together so hard that they
start to touch protons and neutrons
rearrange making long cylinders or
sheets enormous nuclei with millions of
protons and neutrons shaped like
spaghetti and Thea which physicists call
nuclear pasta nuclear pasta is so dense
that it may be the strongest material in
the universe basically
unbreakable lumps of pasta inside a
neutron star can even make mountains at
most a few cenm high but many times as
massive as the
Himalayas eventually beneath the pasta
we reach the core we're not really sure
what the properties of matter are when
they're squeezed this hard protons and
neutrons might dissolve into an ocean of
quarks a so-called Quark gluon plasma
some of those quarks might turn into
strange quarks making a sort of strange
matter with properties so extreme that
we made a whole video about it or maybe
they just stay protons and neutrons no
one knows for sure and that's why we do
science that's all pretty heavy stuff
literally so let's go back out into
space when neutron stars first collapse
they begin to spin very very fast like a
Bina pulling her arms in neutron stars
are Celestial binas spinning many times
per per second this creates pulses
because their magnetic field creates a
beam of radio waves which passes every
time they spin these radio pulsars are
the best known type of neutron star
about 2,000 are known of in the Milky
Way these magnetic fields are the
strongest in the universe a quadrillion
times stronger than Earth's after they
born they're called magners until they
calm down a little but the absolute best
kind of neutron stars are are friends
with other neutron stars by radiating
away energy as gravitational waves
ripples in SpaceTime their orbits can
Decay and they can crash into and kill
each other in a Killin over explosion
that spews out a lot of their guts when
they do the conditions become so extreme
that for a moment heavy nuclei are made
again it's not Fusion putting nuclei
together this time but heavy
neutron-rich matter falling apart and
reassembling only very recently we've
learned that this is probably the origin
of most of the heavy elements in the
universe like gold uranium and platinum
and dozens more so then our two neutron
stars collapse and become a black hole
dying yet
again not only do stars have to die to
create elements they have to die
twice over millions of years these atoms
will mix back into the Galaxy but some
of them end up in a cloud which gravity
pulls together to form stars and planet
repeating the cycle our solar system is
one example and the remains of those
neutron stars that came before us are
all around us our entire technological
modern world was built out of the
elements neutron stars made in eon's
past sending these atoms on a 13 billion
year journey to come together and make
us and our world and that's pretty cool