human existence is scary and confusing a
few hundred thousand years ago we became
conscious and found ourselves in a
strange place it was filled with other
beings we could eat some some could eat
us there was liquid stuff we could drink
things we could use to make more things
the daytime Sky had a tiny yellow ball
that warmed our skin the night sky was
filled with beautiful lights this place
was obviously made for us something was
watching over us we were home this made
everything much less scary and confusing
but the older we got the more we learned
about the world and ourselves we learn
that the twinkling lights are not
shining beautifully for us they just are
we learn that we're not at the center of
what we now call the universe and that
it is much much older than we thought we
learn that we're made of many little
dead things which make up bigger things
that are not dead for some reason and
that we're just another temporary stage
in a history going back over a billion
years we learned in awe that we live on
a moist Speck of dust moving around a
mediumsized star in a quiet region of
one arm of an average Galaxy which is
part of a Galaxy group that we will
never leave and this group is only one
of thousands that together make up a
Galaxy supercluster but even our
supercluster is only one in thousands
that make up what we call the observable
universe the universe might be a million
times bigger but we will never know we
could throw words around like 200
billion galaxies or trillions of stars
or bazillions of planets but all of
these numbers mean nothing our brains
can't comprehend these Concepts the
universe is too big there is too much of
it but size is not the most troubling
concept we have to deal with it's time
or more precisely the time we
have if you're lucky enough to live to
100 you have 5,200 weeks at your
disposal if you're 25 now then you have
3,900 weeks left if you're going to die
at 70 then there are
2340 weeks left a lot of time but also
not really and then what your biological
processes will break down and the
dynamic pattern that is you will stop
being Dynamic it will dissolve until
there is no you left some believe that
there is a part of us we can't see or
measure but we have no way to find out
so this life might be it and we might
end up Dead Forever ever this is less
scary than it sounds though if you don't
remember the 13.75 billion years that
went by before you existed then the
trillions and trillions and trillions of
years that come after will pass in no
time once you're gone close your eyes
count to one that's how long forever
feels and as far as we know in the end
the universe itself will die and nothing
will ever change again our videos induce
existential dread in many people and the
last last few minutes probably haven't
helped so for once we want to offer a
different way of looking at these things
an unscientific subjective point of view
the philosophy of ctz kazak if you want
please take it with a grain of salt we
don't know any more about human
existence than you do we counter
existential dread with optimistic neoism
what do we mean by that well to
summarize it seems very unlikely that
200 trillion trillion stars have been
made for us in a way it feels like the
Cru joke in existence has been played on
us we became self-aware only to realize
this story is not about us while it is
great to know about electrons in the
PowerHouse of the cell science doesn't
do a lot to make this less
depressing okay but so what you only get
one shot at life which is scary but it
also sets you free if the universe ends
in heat death every humiliation you
suffer in your life will be forgotten
every mistake you made will not matter
in the end every bad thing you did will
be voided if our life is all we get to
experience then it's the only thing that
matters if the universe has no
principles the only principles relevant
are the ones we decide on if the
universe has no purpose then we get to
dictate what its purpose is humans will
most certainly cease to exist at some
point but before we do we get to explore
ourselves and the world around us we get
to experience feelings we get to
experience food books sunrises and being
with each other the fact that we're even
able to think about these things is
already kind of incredible it's easy to
think of ourselves as separated from
everything but this is not true we are
as much the universe as a neutron star
or a black hole or a nebula even better
actually we are its thinking and feeling
part the sensory organs of the universe
we are truly free in a universe sized
playground so we might as well aim to be
happy and to build some kind of Utopia
in the star
it's not as if we found out everything
there is to know we don't know why the
rules of the universe are as they are
how life came into existence what life
is we have no idea what Consciousness is
or if we are alone in the universe but
we can try to find some answers there
are billions of stars to visit diseases
to cure people to help Happy Feelings to
be experienced and video games to finish
there is so much to do so wrapping up
you you probably used up a good chunk of
the time available to you if this is our
one shot at life there is no reason not
to have fun and live us happily as
possible bonus points if you make the
life of other people better more bonus
points if you help build a galactic
human Empire do the things that make you
feel good you get to decide whatever
this means for
you it's time to reveal our darkest
secret this may come as a surprise to
you but kazak is not actually run by BBS
but by humans now you might wonder how's
this possible so many people spending
hundreds of hours on research writing
and animating the qut kazak videos that
are then released for free well the
answer is simple it's possible because
of our shop our products are a piece of
quart that you can touch read and have
around you just like our videos they're
a vital part of our dream to inspire
people all around the world our
carefully research to infographic
posters are now part of so many people's
homes teaching them about Evolution
black holes in the night sky while our
gratitude journal helps improve lives
every day a special Thanks goes out to
everyone who appreciates our weirder
product ideas every CTS Kazar product
you buy directly funds another moment we
get to spend working on our videos and
you get a special piece of ctz gazak in
return
thank you so much for being a part of
our story and for making this channel
possible the burp humans of cazar are
eternally grateful
[Music]