never before in history have there been
so many people on earth as right now our
numbers have skyrocketed from 1 billion
in 1800 to 2.3 billion in 1940 3.7
billion in 1970 and 7.4 billion in
2016 the world population increased
four-fold in the last century so what
can we expect for the next century and
what does population growth mean for our
future
will there be Mass migration overcrowded
slums in mega cities covering continents
diseases and pollution chaos and
violence over energy water and food and
a human species focused only on
sustaining itself will population growth
destroy our way of life or is this
prophecy just ungrounded panic
[Music]
in the 1960s population growth reached
an unprecedented rate which led to
apocalyptic
prophecies the poor would procreate
endlessly and overrun the developed
World The Legend of overpopulation was
born but it turns out High birth rates
and the population explosion are not
permanent features of some cultures or
countries but rather part of a four-step
process the whole world is going through
the demographic
transition most developed countries have
already made the transition while other
countries are doing it right now let's
go back to the 18th century when the
entire world including Europe was in the
first stage of the demographic
transition by today's standards Europe
was worse off than a developing region
suffering from poor sanitation poor
diets and poor medicine a lot of people
were born but lots of them died just as
fast so the population hardly grew
women had between four and six children
but only two of them would reach
adulthood then the Industrial Revolution
happened in the UK and brought the
greatest change in human living
conditions since the Agricultural
Revolution people went from being
peasants to
workers manufactured goods were
mass-produced and became widely
available The Sciences flourished and
advanced Transportation communication
and Medicine the role of women in
Society shifted and created the
conditions for their
emancipation slowly this economic
progress not only formed a middle class
but also raised standards of living and
health care for the poor working
population the second transition stage
started better Food Supplies hygiene and
Medicine meant people stopped dying all
the time especially so at a very young
age the result was a population
explosion doubling the UK's population
between 1750 and 1850
the main reason families used to have
lots of children was that only a few of
them were likely to survive now that had
changed so the third stage of the
transition was set in motion fewer
babies were conceived and population
growth slowed
down eventually a balance emerged fewer
people were dying and fewer children
were born so the death rate and birth
rate became stable Britain had reached
the fourth stage of the demographic
transition this didn't only happen in
the UK more more and more countries went
through the four
stages first many births and many deaths
due to bad living conditions second
better living conditions leading to
fewer deaths and a population explosion
third fewer deaths resulting in fewer
births and population growth came to an
end but if birth rates have dropped so
much why is the population still growing
so fast well the children born in the
population explosion of the 70s and '
80s are having kids themselves now
leading to a noticeable will spike in
overall population but they are having
far fewer children on average than their
parents the average today is 2.5 it was
5 40 years ago so as this generation
gets older and fertility declines
further the rate of population growth
will keep on
slowing this is true for every country
in the west we tend to overlook progress
in other regions of the world but
actually most of the world's countries
have made it to the fourth stage just
look at Bangladesh in 1971 the average
woman had seven kids but 25% of them
would die before the age of five in 2015
the mortality rate was down to 3.8% and
women had only 2.2 kids on
average this is the rule not an
exception we're not special we just had
a head start it took developed countries
about 80 years to reduce fertility from
more than six children to less than
three others are catching up fast
Malaysia and South Africa did it in only
30 4 years Bangladesh took just 20 Iran
Managed IT in 10 years all these
countries that are catching up didn't
have to start from scratch and the more
support they get the faster they catch
up this is why programs that help lower
child mortality or help poor Nations
develop are so important no matter what
your motivation is whether you dream of
a world where all people live in Freedom
and wealth or you just want fewer
refugees coming to your country the
simple truth is that it's beneficial to
you personally if people on the other
side of the Globe can live a good
life and we are getting there the
percentage of people living in extreme
poverty has never been as low as
today so the future of global population
growth is actually not an apocalyptic
prophecy at all it's a promise
population growth will come to an end
the UN forecasts that the 12th billionth
human will never be born at
all and as the development level of the
world Rises the number of people with a
higher education will increase tfold
countries who used to be in need will
help Advance development
instead more people is going to mean
more people able to advance our
[Music]
species this video was a collaboration
with Max Rosa and our world in data
where he explores the progress of
humanity through research and data
visualization make sure to check it out
in 2016 we were able to make more and
better content than ever before because
of your support on patreon.com thank you
so much and we'll be back in the year