Around one in three of you could suffer
from a panic attack at least once in
your life. This tsunami of horrible
feelings can hit you out of the blue.
Your brain and body suddenly decide
you're in danger even though you felt
okay a minute ago. Your amydala sounds
the alarm, prompting the release of
adrenaline, which causes symptoms like a
racing heart, shortness of breath, and
even a deep sense of dread. Panic
attacks can be triggered by stress, a
shocking life event, or even too much
nicotine, caffeine, or alcohol.
So, what can you do? Even if it feels
awful, know that the panic won't
physically hurt you and that the attack
will pass. Try not to fight it. And if
you can, slow your breathing and focus
on what's around you. The adrenaline
you've produced will soon be metabolized
and absorbed. As soon as this happens,
you'll start to feel better. After an
attack, try doing things that put you
more at ease, like talking with a
friend, taking a walk, and you may
consider professional help. Most
importantly, be kind to yourself. It's
okay to be scared and you're not alone.