welcome to EA Homeschool
Academy today we will learn about the
moon have you ever looked into the night
sky to see the Wonder and beauty of the
stars and the
moon have you ever wondered why the Moon
is there and why it seems to change each
night well let's learn all about the
moon
today
the Moon is one of the brightest objects
in our night sky and it orbits or moves
around the earth much like how the Earth
orbits the sun it takes the moon
approximately 27 days or 1 month to
complete its orbit around the
Earth the Moon is more than one4 the
size of Earth and is made mostly of rock
its surface has thousands of pits called
craters which are for formed when chunks
of rock and metal called meteorites
crash into
it during the day when the sun is facing
the moon the surface temperature is
about
225° F or 107° C but at night it drops
to -
243° F or
-13°
C the moon does not produce its own
light instead it reflect cols the light
from the sun depending on its position
in the sky part of it will be lit up and
part of it will be dark depending on its
position in the lunar cycle it will
appear in different shapes and this is
what we refer to as the phases of the
moon the lunar cycle begins with the new
moon when the moon appears completely
dark this is because the unlet side of
the moon is completely facing the
Earth solar eclipses can only happen
during the new moon phase because it is
the only time that the Moon is between
the Sun and the Earth the second phase
in the mooner cycle is called the waxing
Cresent the moon will appear with a thin
slice of light in the shape of a
crescent at this point in the lunar
cycle the moon appears to be growing
hence the term wax and Crescent
the third phase in the lunar cycle is
called the first
quarter the Crescent in the second phase
would have gotten thicker revealing
about half of the Moon by this
point some people refer to the Moon as a
half moon but the more accurate term to
use is first quarter since the Moon is
one quarter of the way through its
cycle the fourth phase of the lunar
cycle is called the waxin gibbus the
word gibbus means swollen and the word
waxin means growing so in this phase the
moon appears to be growing even more
with each passing
day the fifth phase of the lunar cycle
is called the full moon in this phase
the Moon is the biggest the brightest
and the most
noticeable at this point during the
lunar cycle the Moon is halfway through
its orbit around the Earth
this is the only time that there can be
a lunar eclipse because it is the only
time the Earth's Shadow would fall on
the moon with each passing day the moon
appears
smaller the sixth phase of the moon is
called the waning gibbus the word waning
means to shrink or get smaller so as the
moon continues its orbit it appears to
get smaller each day the seventh phase
of the moon is called the third quarter
because the Moon is 3/4 of the way
through its orbit around the Earth half
of the moon is covered in this phas the
moon appears to get smaller with each
passing
day the eighth phase of the moon is
called the waning crescent as the moon
appears to shrink down to a thin sliver
of light it nears the end of its orbit
around the Earth with each passing day
the light completely Fades until the
moon transitions completely into the new
moon and the cycle starts
again the moon has been a fascinating
and intriguing object in our night sky
for a long time it is a natural
permanent satellite for earth and its
gravity affects our planet the moon's
gravitational pull affects our ocean
levels which creates high and low tide
conditions the moon is big beautiful and
bright it may appear different each
night as it completes its orbit around
the
Earth now you know the various phases of
the moon can you name them
all new
moon waxing
crescent
first
quarter waxing
gibbus full
moon waning
gibbus third
quarter waning
crescent I hope you learned something
about the moon today thanks for taking
this Learning Journey with me until next
time as always thank you for watching
tell us what you want to see next email
EA Homeschool Academy at
yahoo.com like and share our videos
please subscribe to our Channel