when the gods granted King Midas one
wish he wished that everything he
touched would turn to gold
Midas was delighted trees rocks
buildings all gold but soon he found in
horror that his food turned into gold as
well when he hugged his daughter to
soothe his pain he realized his mistake
too late
the richest man in existence was
starving heartbroken and alone
Humanity got a similar wish granted when
we learned how to turn Brown's stinky
goo into magic plastic cheap sterile and
convenient it changed our lives
but this Wonder of Technology got a
little out of hand
plastic has saturated our environment it
has invaded the animals we eat and now
it's finding its way into our bodies
[Music]
what is plastic
for most of our history humans use stuff
we found in nature to build the things
we needed but the invention of plastic
roughly 100 years ago completely changed
our world plastic is made from polymers
long repeating chains of molecule groups
in nature polymers exist everywhere the
walls of cells Silk Hair insect
carapaces DNA but it's also possible to
create them by breaking down crude oil
into its components and rearranging them
we can form new synthetic polymers
synthetic polymers have extraordinary
traits they are lightweight durable and
can be molded into almost any shape not
requiring time-consuming manual work
plastic can be easily mass-produced and
its raw materials are available in vast
amounts and Incredibly cheaply and so
the Golden Era of plastics began
Baker light was used for mechanical
Parts PVC for plumbing electric gears
and cases acrylic has a shatter
resistant alternative to Glass and nylon
for stockings and War equipment today
almost everything is at least partly
made from plastic our clothes phones
computers Furniture appliances houses
and cars plastic has long ceased to be a
revolutionary material instead it became
trash
coffee cups plastic bags or stuff to
wrap a banana we don't think about this
fact a lot plastic just appears and goes
away
unfortunately it doesn't
since synthetic polymers are so durable
plastic takes between 500 and 1 000
years to break down but somehow we
collectively decided to use this super
tough material for things meant to be
thrown away
40 of plastics are used for packaging
in the U.S packaging makes up one third
of all the waste that is generated
annually since its invention we have
produced about 8.3 billion metric tons
of plastic
335 million tons in 2016 alone more than
6.3 billion metric tons of plastic have
become waste since 1907 piled up in one
place that makes a cube with a side
length of 1.9 kilometers so what did we
do with all this waste nine percent was
recycled 12 burnt but 79 of it is
sticking around still
a lot ends up in the ocean around 8
million tons a year that's so much
plastic that it will outweigh all the
fish in the ocean by 2050.
because it's everywhere marine animals
keep getting trapped in plastic and
swallowing it in 2015 already 90 percent
of seabirds had eaten plastic many
animals starve with stomachs full of
indigestible trash in 2018 a dead sperm
whale washed up in Spain he had eaten 32
kilos of plastic bags Nets and a drum
while this is tragic and makes for great
magazine covers there's an even more
widespread invisible form of plastic
microplastics
microplastics are pieces smaller than
five millimeters some of them are used
in cosmetics or toothpaste but most
result from floating waste that is
constantly exposed to UV radiation and
crumbles into smaller and smaller pieces
51 trillion such particles float in the
ocean where they are even more easily
swallowed by all kinds of marine life
this has raised concerns among
scientists especially about health risks
from the chemicals that are added to
plastic BPA for example makes plastic
bottles transparent but there's also
evidence that it interferes with our
hormonal system
dehp makes Plastics more flexible but
may cause cancer
it would be pretty bad if microplastics
are toxic because they travel up the
food chain
zooplankton eat microplastic small fish
eat zooplankton soda oysters crabs and
predatory fish and they all land on our
plate
microplastics have been found in Honey
in sea salt in beer in tap water and in
the household dust around us
8 out of 10 babies and nearly all adults
have measurable amounts of phthalates a
common plastic additive in their bodies
and 93 percent of people have BPA in
their urine there is little science
about this so far and right now it's
inconclusive we need a lot more research
before Panic is Justified but it is safe
to say that a lot of stuff happened that
we didn't plan for and we have lost
control over plastic to a certain extent
which is kind of scary
but just to make sure we should simply
ban Plastics right unfortunately it's a
bit more complicated than that plastic
pollution is not the only environmental
challenge we Face some of the
substitutes we'd use for plastic have a
higher environmental impact in other
ways for example according to a recent
study by the Danish government making a
single-use plastic bag requires so
little energy and produces far lower
carbon dioxide emissions compared to a
reusable cotton bag that you need to use
your cotton bag
7100 times before it would have a lower
impact on the environment than the
plastic bag we're left with a complex
process of trade-offs everything has an
impact somehow and it's hard to find the
right balance between them
plastic also helps solve problems that
we don't have very good answers for at
the moment globally one-third of all
food that's produced is never eaten and
ends up rotting away on landfills where
it produces methane and the best way of
preventing food from spoiling and
avoiding unnecessary waste is still
plastic packaging it's also important to
know whether vast majority of the
world's plastic pollution is coming from
right now ninety percent of all plastic
waste entering the ocean Through Rivers
comes from just 10 rivers in Asia and
Africa the Yangtze in China alone
flushes 1.5 million tons of plastic into
the ocean each year countries like China
India Algeria or Indonesia
industrialized at an impressive Pace in
the last few decades transforming the
lives of billions of people this
development was so fast that the garbage
disposal infrastructure couldn't keep up
with collecting and recycling all the
new waste this brought if politicians in
Europe and the US want to address this
issue investing in infrastructure in
developing countries is just as
important as fighting plastic pollution
at home with campaigns and redesigning
products to minimize unnecessary plastic
production the bottom line is as long as
we don't address plastic pollution from
a Global Perspective we will not Solve
IT plastic pollution is a complicated
problem
we found a magic material and we had a
really good time with it but we need to
be careful or just like Midas we'll end
up in a world that we didn't wish for
your individual daily actions still have
a huge impact what you do matters
refuse disposable Plastics convince your
friends and family to do the same
pressure companies and politicians to
take the necessary steps to keep our
oceans clean and our food safe together
we can beat plastic pollution this video
was a collaboration with un environment
and their clean Seas campaign if you
want to take action to turn the tide on
Plastics go to cleances.org and make
your pledge