for most of our history human technology
consisted of our brains fire and sharp
sticks while fire and sharp sticks
became power plants and nuclear weapons
the biggest upgrade has happened to our
brains since the 1960s the power of our
brain machines has kept growing
exponentially allowing computers to get
smaller and more powerful at the same
time but this process is about to meet
its physical limits computer parts are
approaching the size of an atom to
understand why this is a problem we have
to clear up some
[Music]
Basics a computer is made up of very
simple components doing very simple
things representing data the means of
processing it and control mechanisms
computer chips contain modules which
contain logic gates which contain
transistors a transistor is the simplest
form of a data processor in computers
basically a switch that can either block
or open the way for information coming
through this information is made up of
bits which can be set to either zero or
one combinations of several bits are
used to represent more complex
information transistors are combined to
create logic gates which still do very
simple stuff for example an and gate
sends an output of one if all of its
inputs are one and an output of zero
otherwise combinations of logic gates
finally form meaningful modules say for
adding two numbers once you can add you
can also multiply and once you can
multiply you can basically do anything
since all basic operations are literally
simpler than first grade math you can
imagine a computer as a group of
seven-year-olds answering really basic
math questions a large enough bunch of
them could compute anything from
astrophysics to Zelda however with parts
getting tinier and tinier quantum
physics are making things tricky in a
nutshell a transistor is just an
electric switch electricity is electrons
moving from one place to another so a
switch is a passage that can block
electrons from moving in One Direction
today a typical scale for transistors is
40 NM which is about 8 times less than
the HIV virus's diameter and 500 times
smaller than a red blood cells as
transistors are shrinking to the size of
only a few atoms electrons may just
transfer themselves to the other side of
a blocked passage via a process called
Quantum tunneling in the quantum Realm
physics Works quite differently from the
predictable ways we're used to and
traditional computers just stop making
sense we are approaching a real physical
barrier for our technological progress
to solve this problem scientists are
trying to use these unusual Quantum
properties to their advantage by
building quantum computers in normal
computers bits are the smallest units of
information quantum computers use cubits
which can also be set to one of two
values a cubit can be any two level
Quantum system such as a spin in a
magnetic field or a single Photon zero
and one of this system's possible States
like the photon's horizontal or vertical
polarization in the quantum world the
Cubit doesn't have to be in just one of
those it can be in any proportions of
both States at once this is called
superp position but as soon as you test
its value Say by sending the photon
through a filter it has to decide to be
either vertically or horizontally
polarized so as long as it's unobserved
the cubid is in a superp position of
probabilities for zero and one and you
can't predict which it will be but the
instance you measure it it collapses
into one of the definite States superp
position is a GameChanger for classical
bits can be in one of two to the power
of four different configurations at a
time that's 16 possible combinations out
of which you can use just one four
cubits in superp position however can be
in all of those 16 combinations at once
this number grows exponentially with
each extra Cubit 20 of them can already
store a million values in parallel a
really weird and unintuitive property
cubits can have is entanglement a close
connection that makes each of the cubits
react to a change in the other's State
instantaneously no matter how far they
are apart this means that when measuring
just one entangled Cubit you can
directly deduce properties of its
Partners without having to look Cubit
manipulation is a mind Bender as well a
normal logic gate gets a simple set of
inputs and produces one definite output
a Quantum gate manipulates an input of
superp positions rotates probabilities
and produces another superposition as
its output so a quantum computer sets up
some cubits applies Quantum gates to
entangle them and manipulate
probabilities and finally measures the
outcome collapsing superpositions to an
actual sequence of zeros and ones what
this means is that you get the entire
lot of calculations that are possible
with your setup all done at the same
time ultimately you can only measure one
of the results and it will only probably
be the one you want so you may have to
double check and try
again but by cleverly exploiting superp
position and entanglement this can be
exponentially more efficient than would
ever be possible on a normal
computer so while quantum computers will
probably not replace our home computers
in some areas they are vastly superior
one of them is dat database searching to
find something in a database a normal
computer may have to test every single
one of its entries Quantum algorithms
need only the square root of that time
which for large databases is a huge
difference the most famous use of
quantum computers is ruining it security
right now your browsing email and
banking data is being kept secure by an
encryption system in which you give
everyone a public key to encode messages
only you can decode the problem is that
this public key can actually be used to
calculate your secret private key
luckily doing the necessary math on any
normal computer would literally take
years of trial and error but a quantum
computer with exponential speed up could
do it in a breeze another really
exciting new use is simulations
simulations of the quantum world are
very intense on resources and even for
bigger structures such as molecules they
often lack accuracy so why not simulate
quantum physics with actual quantum
physics quantum simulations could
provide new insights on proteins that
might revolutionize medicine right now
we don't know if quantum computers will
be just a very specialized tool or a big
revolution for Humanity we have no idea
where the limits of Technology are and
there's only one way to find
out this video is supported by the
Australian Academy of Science which
promotes and supports excellence in
science learn more about this topic and
others like it at nova.org AU it was a
blast to work with them so go check out
their site our videos are also made
possible by your support on
patreon.com if you want to support us
and become part of the kots gazak bird
Army check out our patreon page
[Music]